<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The plain Englishman's historian, or, A compendious chronicle of England from its first being inhabited to this present year 1679 but more especially containing the chief remarques of all our Kings and Queens since the conquest, their lives and reigns, policies, wars, laws, successes, and troubles : with the most notable accidents, as dearths, tempests, monstrous births, and other prodigies that happened in each of their times respectively / by H.C.</title>
            <author>H. C., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B18413</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8095946</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204203</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264207065</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C45</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08095946</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B18413)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204203)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1224:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The plain Englishman's historian, or, A compendious chronicle of England from its first being inhabited to this present year 1679 but more especially containing the chief remarques of all our Kings and Queens since the conquest, their lives and reigns, policies, wars, laws, successes, and troubles : with the most notable accidents, as dearths, tempests, monstrous births, and other prodigies that happened in each of their times respectively / by H.C.</title>
                  <author>H. C., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 141 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Langley Curtis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204203:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204203:2"/>
            <p>THE Plain Englishman's Historian: OR, A Compendious Chronicle OF ENGLAND, From its first being Inhabited to this present Year 1679.</p>
            <p>But more especially containing the chief Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marques of all our Kings and Queens since the Conquest, their Lives and Reigns, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, Wars, Laws, Successes, and Troubles.</p>
            <p>With the most Notable Accidents, as Dearths, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests, Monstrous Births, and other Prodigies that happened in each of their times respectively.</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. C.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Non Multa, sed Multum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Langley Curtis</hi> in Goat Court on <hi>Ludgate-hill.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:204203:3"/>
            <p>Licensed <hi>Aug.</hi> 9. 1678.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Roger L'Estrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:204203:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:204203:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204203:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTL TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS the Mind of man is generally desirous of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> so there is scarce any Humane Knowledge more pleasant or useful than that of <hi>History,</hi> especially of our own Native <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> which representing the brave Actions of our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, stirs up our thoughts with a generous Emulation to Glorious Attempts; and
<pb facs="tcp:204203:5"/>by recording the disastrous ends of <hi>Rebellion, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, Oppression, Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp;c.</hi> plants in us a just abhorrence and detestation of such <hi>odious practices,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing us with lively pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of Heroick Vertues, like <hi>Baits</hi> to allure us, and eminent <hi>Examples</hi> of Gods Justice, as <hi>Sea-marks</hi> to warn us, whilest adorning with never fading flowers the Tombs of our <hi>Ancestors,</hi> and rescuing their Names from <hi>Oblivion and Dust.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:204203:5"/>It exalts flitting <hi>Time</hi> to a kind of <hi>Immortality,</hi> and digests <hi>barbarous Tradition</hi> into <hi>useful Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis both a pity and a shame to see so many people <hi>utterly ignorant</hi> in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Countrey, and I have often lamented the ill Conduct of our <hi>Youth,</hi> who fool away their time in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing silly Romances, that fill their heads with extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, and oft-times <hi>baneful</hi> Whimsies, whilest they might as easily stock their Minds
<pb facs="tcp:204203:6"/>with <hi>useful Notions:</hi> For I do not understand that there is much more <hi>Capacity</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to apprehend the <hi>great Acts</hi> of our several <hi>Princes</hi> since the Conquest, than to remember the <hi>fabulous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits</hi> of the <hi>Seven Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions,</hi> or the <hi>ridiculous Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures</hi> of <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Sir Bevis.</hi> Nor know I, but a Child may improve his <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> and delight his <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> as much in the <hi>real and mighty Victories</hi> of <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>3<seg rend="sup">d.</seg>
               </hi> or <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>5<seg rend="sup">th</seg>.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:204203:6"/>as in the <hi>imaginary at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements</hi> of <hi>Parismus</hi> or the <hi>Knight of the Sun, Heros</hi> that never had <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> but in the <hi>fantastick Region</hi> of some <hi>idle Brain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To promote these <hi>more solid and beneficial Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> I here present the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with <hi>a very brief Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of English History,</hi> whose <hi>bulk</hi> can neither <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> nor its <hi>price impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish thee:</hi> and yet (if I <hi>mistake</hi> not) thou mayest therein <hi>at once take an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb facs="tcp:204203:7"/>view</hi> (though as in <hi>Landskip</hi>) of the <hi>most considerable affairs</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in our <hi>Chronicles.</hi> There have been several <hi>Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>says</hi> in this kind heretofore, but 'tis conceived none with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>divers mistakes,</hi> or at least <hi>not aiming at,</hi> or <hi>so briefly accomplishing</hi> the <hi>Ends</hi> designed by these <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections;</hi> but of that let the <hi>Judicious</hi> censure, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all charitably pardon <hi>any defects or errors,</hi> which pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly he may meet with:
<pb facs="tcp:204203:7"/>Though in <hi>compiling</hi> it I consulted most of <hi>our best Historians,</hi> as voluminous <hi>Hollingshead,</hi> diligent but sometimes trifling <hi>Stow,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious <hi>Speed,</hi> and (who is <hi>instar omnium</hi>) Judicious Sir <hi>Richard Baker,</hi> whose <hi>Chronicle</hi> I cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to thy <hi>perusal,</hi> if thou hast <hi>leisure and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> as the <hi>best</hi> yet extant, to accomplish thee in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish History.</hi> As for this present <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> 'twill be enough if it <hi>serve thee as
<pb facs="tcp:204203:8"/>a Table of general Affairs,</hi> with the <hi>exact times</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they happened: Its <hi>chief use</hi> designed being, to be read <hi>before larger Histories</hi> as a <hi>Preparative,</hi> or <hi>after them</hi> as a <hi>Recapitulation;</hi> and yet even <hi>alone</hi> it will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the <hi>plain Englishman,</hi> that has not time for <hi>tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reading,</hi> with such a <hi>competent stock of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> as no other <hi>Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in this kind of <hi>so small a price</hi> can pretend to; and consequently may justifie its Title, and deserve his thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acceptance. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204203:8"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Plain Mans English</hi> HISTORIAN.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The State of</hi> Britain <hi>before the Conquest, under the</hi> Britains, Romans, Saxons, <hi>and</hi> Danes.</head>
               <p>THough the Story of <hi>Brute</hi> be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the best Authors fabulous, as first hatcht by <hi>Geofry</hi> of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth;</hi> yet since it has much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained credit in the vulgar Creed, we shall give you the Traditional Account of it, which is,</p>
               <p>That <hi>Brute,</hi> descended from <hi>Aeneas,</hi> with a Troop of <hi>Trojans</hi> landed here about the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204203:9"/>year of the World 2855, and near eleven hundred years before the Incarnation of our Saviour, being in the time of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet. The Kinsman of this <hi>Brute, Cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> by name, conquering <hi>Gogmagog</hi> a Giant, and flinging him off from <hi>Dover</hi> Cliff into the Sea, they soon subdued the whole Island, and built <hi>London,</hi> which in memory of their former Country, they called <hi>New-Troy.</hi> When <hi>Brute</hi> died he gave to his eldest Son <hi>Locrine, England;</hi> to <hi>Cambrius, Wales;</hi> and to <hi>Albanact, Scotland;</hi> to whom succeeded many Kings, but of their Acts there is little of Truth recorded.</p>
               <p>The most considerable Adventure of which we have certainty, was that of the Roman General <hi>Julius Caesar,</hi> who having (much about 50 years before Christ) conquered <hi>France,</hi> attempted <hi>Britain;</hi> and was at first manfully repulsed, but afterwards made it submit in a great measure to that resistless Fortune which had triumphed over the rest of the World, though the whole were not subdued till the time of <hi>Domitian,</hi> almost 200 years after. The Country was so well liked by the <hi>Romans,</hi> that several of their Emperours came hither in person, as <hi>Adrian</hi> in the year of Christ 124, and <hi>Severus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most an hundred years after. And what is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204203:9"/>more considerable, the Great <hi>Constantine</hi> first <hi>Christian Emperour</hi> in the World, was both born here, and first saluted Emperour at <hi>York:</hi> But after the Land had remained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Romans near 500 years, they being imbroyl'd at home slighted it, and <hi>Vortiger</hi> King of the <hi>Britains</hi> oppressed by the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> about the year of Christ 448. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the <hi>Saxons,</hi> a people of <hi>Germany,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conduct of two Brothers <hi>Hengist</hi> and <hi>Horsa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But first we must Note, That 'tis said this Island received the <hi>Christian Faith</hi> long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, even in the year 63, by the preaching of <hi>Joseph</hi> of <hi>Arimathaea,</hi> who lies buried, they report, at <hi>Glassenbury.</hi> 'Tis certain <hi>England</hi> was honoured with the first <hi>Christian King</hi> that we read of in the World, <hi>viz. Lucius,</hi> in the year 180. But these <hi>Saxons</hi> were Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and having beat off the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> according to the custom of foreign Auxiliaries, usurped the Dominion of the Land to themselves; but in the Reign of King <hi>Ethelbert, Anno</hi> 596. were converted to Christianity, and in some time afterwards erected seven Kingdoms in this Island, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> that is to say, That of <hi>Kent</hi> of the <hi>South-Saxons</hi> containing <hi>Sussex</hi> and <hi>Surrey;</hi> of the <hi>West-Saxons</hi> from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204203:10"/>
                  <hi>Bark-shire</hi> to <hi>Cornwal;</hi> of the <hi>East-Saxons</hi> being <hi>Essex</hi> and <hi>Middlesex;</hi> of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> including <hi>York-shire, &amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Mercia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the In-land Counties; and of the East-Angles, <hi>viz. Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Norfolk,</hi> so that in the Reign of <hi>Cadwallader</hi> in the year 689. the <hi>Britains</hi> had lost almost all, and were forced to retreat into the Mountains of <hi>Wales,</hi> where their Posterity remains to this day. And about the year 818. <hi>Egbert</hi> King of the <hi>West-Saxons</hi> reducing the other petty Kings to his obedience, caused all the South parts to be called <hi>ENGLAND</hi> from the <hi>Angles,</hi> a species of the <hi>Saxons</hi> from whom he was descended.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>how short-liv'd is worldly power!</hi> The <hi>Saxons</hi> had no sooner thus compleated their Conquest, but the <hi>Danes</hi> began to infest them, and though often beaten back, got in time possession, exercising all kind of rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and cruelties, for resisting of which, rare is the Example of the Nuns of <hi>Coldingham,</hi> who to avoid being ravisht by these Pagans, voluntarily <hi>cut off their own Lips and Noses,</hi> chusing rather Deformity than Pollution.</p>
               <p>About the year 900. reigned King <hi>Alfred</hi> a Prince of extraordinary vertues, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten triumphed over the <hi>Danes,</hi> and first of all for more Civil Government, divided the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204203:10"/>Land into <hi>Shires, Hundreds,</hi> and <hi>Tythings,</hi> and so suppressed Robbers, that 'tis said, A Child might have travell'd with a Bag of Gold or Silver from one end of <hi>England</hi> to another without molestation; but still and long after the <hi>Danes</hi> retain'd their foot-hold, and at last prevailed so far, as to insult over the <hi>English</hi> as their Slaves, sitting idle and abusing their Wives and Daughters at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, whilest the others only labour'd in Tillage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> so that they were generally termed <hi>Lord-Danes</hi> (whence to this day we call an Idle-pack, a <hi>Lurdan</hi>) whereupon King <hi>Ethelred</hi> to shake off their yoak, granted a secret Commission to all parts of his Realm, that at such a prefixt time they should Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre all the <hi>Danes,</hi> which was performed (and, as 'tis said, altogether by the women) on the thirteenth of <hi>November,</hi> 1002. But this (like to <hi>violent Physick</hi>) did more <hi>harm</hi> than <hi>good;</hi> for herewith the <hi>Danes</hi> more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asperated, came over in greater numbers, and at last <hi>Canutus</hi> (by aid of the treacherous <hi>Edrick</hi> against King <hi>Edmund,</hi> surnamed <hi>Ironside,</hi> whom he perfidiously slew) obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the whole Kingdom, and as the first Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Monarch, was crowned at <hi>London</hi> in the year 1017. He made many good Laws, as that the Sabbath should be strictly observed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204203:11"/>(for now the <hi>Danes</hi> were converted:) That the Communion should be received thrice a year; and that a Woman convicted of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, should have her Nose and Ears cut off; whence, perhaps, our jealous Wives custom of marking such as they suppose to be their Husbands Harlots, may take origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. This Princes Flatterers would tell him his power was more than Humane (indeed he was a mighty Monarch.) To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their vanity, being at <hi>Southampton,</hi> he caused his Chair of State to be set on the Sand at young Flood, and said in a Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick tone to the approaching Element, <hi>I charge thee that thou presume not to flow any higher, nor wet my Royal Robes;</hi> but the stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Ocean continuing its course, wet first his Skirt, and next himself up to the middle, whereupon arising (as it was but time) in haste, he said in presence of them all, <hi>You see how vain is the Power of mortal Kings, and that none is worthy of your Applause, but he who made and keeps both Heaven, Earth, and Sea in Awe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Canutus</hi> dying, left his Kingdom of <hi>Norway</hi> to his eldest Son <hi>Sweyne,</hi> and to <hi>Hardiknute England,</hi> but he being absent, one <hi>Harold,</hi> an elder Brother by a former wife succeeds for four years, and then dying
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204203:11"/>without Issue, <hi>Hardiknute</hi> is invited over, and accepts the Crown in the year 1040. being surnamed for his Gluttony <hi>Swynes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi> Nor was his <hi>End</hi> unlike his <hi>Life,</hi> for soon after he fell down dead in a solemn Banquet at <hi>Lambeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After him succeeded <hi>Edward,</hi> surnamed the Confessor, but not of the Danish Line, but Son to King <hi>Ethelred</hi> by his wife Queen <hi>Emma,</hi> crowned on Easter Day, 1042, he was after his Fathers Death bred up in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> where grew the acquaintance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and Duke <hi>William,</hi> and thence at forty years of Age was sent for, to take the English Crown; a Prince very diligent in compiling a Body of Laws, and adjusting the forms of Process and Pleadings; he was the first that exercised the Gift (ever since inherent in our English Kings) of Healing the Disease called the <hi>Evil,</hi> by Touching; and, 'tis said, suspecting his Mother of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency, put her to the tryal by <hi>Ordeal,</hi> which was to pass blindfold and barefooted over nine Plow-Shares red-hot laid in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal distance, which she in testimony of her Innocency perform'd unhurt.</p>
               <p>After he had reign'd 23 years and six months, he ended his life in the Painted Chamber at <hi>Westminster,</hi> leaving behind him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204203:12"/>no Issue; though he had designed <hi>Edgar</hi> Grandson of <hi>Edmund Ironside</hi> to succeed, but he being young, <hi>Harold</hi> the Son of Earl <hi>Goodwin</hi> justled him beside the Throne, and filled the place in his stead, it being said, That King <hi>Edward</hi> before his Death had appointed the Crown variously, sometimes to <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> sometimes to the said <hi>Edgar,</hi> and sometimes to this <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold,</hi> who being upon the place, and a very Martial Man, counting his Right equal to either of theirs, was easily induced by kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to himself to prefer it before them both, and so took upon him the Crown, which yet he enjoyed but nine months, and that with great trouble, and then was slain by <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Normandy.</hi> It seems the Family was unfortunate, or rather justly punished for their sins, for his Father Earl <hi>Goodwin</hi> having caused King <hi>Edwards</hi> Brother to be murdered, it happened many years after, as he sate at Dinner with the King in <hi>Windsor</hi>-Castle, the Kings Cup-bearer stumbled, &amp; not without much difficulty, recovered himself from falling, whereupon the Earl laught hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and said, <hi>There one Brother helped the other,</hi> meaning one Leg supported the other, which the King observing, said, <hi>Yea, and so my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Alfred <hi>might have lived to have assisted me,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204203:12"/>had it not been for Earl Goodwin.</hi> Whereupon the Earl to excuse himself, wisht if he were not innocent of that Princes death, a piece of Bread he was going to swallow might <hi>choak</hi> him, with which he was choaked indeed, and fell down dead at the Table; and shortly after all his Lands in <hi>Kent</hi> were eaten up and swallowed by the Sea, being that dangerous Coast, which from his Name to this day is called <hi>Goodwin</hi>'s <hi>Sands.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of</hi> William <hi>the Conquerour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIlliam</hi> the Natural Son of <hi>Robert</hi> Duke <hi>Normandy,</hi> by <hi>Arlotte</hi> a Skinners Daughter (from whom, 'tis thought, such kind Souls are called <hi>Harlots</hi>) on pretence of a gift of the Crown from <hi>Edward</hi> the Confessor his Kinsman, invades <hi>England</hi> with a great Navy, and threescore thousand men, landing at <hi>Pemsey</hi> in <hi>Sussex;</hi> and on the fourteenth of <hi>October</hi> in the year, 1066. after a fierce and bloody fight, (wherein he himself had three Horses killed under him) vanquishes and kills <hi>Harold</hi> the then usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping King of <hi>England,</hi> and is crowned King,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204203:13"/>taking an Oath to observe King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the first year of his Reign he laid a grievous Tax on his Subjects, seized on the Money and Plate of the Religious Houses, and that he might know what every man was worth, caused a particular Account of all Estates to be taken and recorded, called <hi>Doomsday-Book.</hi> He caused all Pleas to be in French, and instituted the Four <hi>Terms,</hi> whereas Controversies before were decided monthly in the Hundred Courts.</p>
               <p>In the third year of his Reign was so great a <hi>Famine,</hi> that men were forced to eat Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, Dogs, Cats, Rats, and all sorts of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and Carrion.</p>
               <p>In his thirteenth year he subdued <hi>Wales,</hi> having before made <hi>Malcome</hi> King of <hi>Scots</hi> do him Homage. In his time Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh first ordained that Priests should have no more Wives, and such as had them already, should either be divorced or lose their Benefices.</p>
               <p>His eldest Son <hi>Robert,</hi> whom he had left behind in <hi>Normandy,</hi> by the counsel and aid of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> invades and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to usurp that Dukedom against his Father in his life, who had promised him the same after his death. At which King
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204203:13"/>
                  <hi>William</hi> being grievously enraged, went over and gave him Battel, in which it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd, that <hi>Robert</hi> unawares encountred singly with his Father, and beat him down to the ground; but then knowing him by his voice, flung himself from his Horse at his feet, begging his Pardon, which the King readily granted; so they were recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled: yet 'tis observed, that <hi>Robert</hi> did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thrive after this unnatural Rebellion, but died, as we shall see afterwards, most mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably.</p>
               <p>This King being much delighted in Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, made <hi>New Forrest</hi> in <hi>Hampshire,</hi> (cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down and depopulating six and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fair Towns, many Churches, and four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score Religious Houses for the space of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty miles for that purpose; which he stockt with wild Beasts, making sharp. Laws for the maintainance and encrease of the same; but we may take notice, <hi>he had two Sons came to untimely ends in that very For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest,</hi> viz. <hi>Richard</hi> in his own life time, and <hi>William Rufus</hi> afterwards.</p>
               <p>Being engaged in a War with <hi>France,</hi> by heat and leaping a Ditch on Horse-back he fell into a sickness, and died at <hi>Roan</hi> the ninth of <hi>September,</hi> 1687. having reign'd twenty years and near eleven months, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204203:14"/>three Sons, <hi>Robert</hi> to whom he gave <hi>Normandy, William</hi> whom he appointed King of <hi>England, Henry</hi> to whom he gave five thousand pound in money, though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he got to be King, and one daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter named <hi>Adela,</hi> married to <hi>Stephen</hi> Earl of <hi>Blois,</hi> and Mother to <hi>Stephen</hi> afterwards King.</p>
               <p>He was buried at <hi>Caen</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> but when his Corps was just ready to be interr'd, one <hi>Anselm Fitz-Arthur</hi> interrupted it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leading the Ground was the Floor of his Fathers House, unjustly wrested from him by this King <hi>William,</hi> so that they were forced to give him an hundred pound for Composition before they could bury him. <hi>Thus Conquerours who think the world too little for themselves living, can scarce get room for a Grave when Dead.</hi> 'Tis recorded for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That the very same day he died at <hi>Roan,</hi> his death was known at <hi>Rome,</hi> being a thousand Miles off. A little before his death there happened a terrible Fire in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> consuming all along from <hi>Algate</hi> to <hi>Ludgate;</hi> and likewise in his time a great Lord sitting at a Feast, was set upon by <hi>Mice,</hi> and though he were removed from Land to Sea, and from Sea to Land, yet the <hi>Mice</hi> still followed him, and at last devoured him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:204203:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Life and Reign of</hi> William Rufus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIlliam</hi> the second of that name, sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Rufus</hi> (that is to say the Red) was crowned the fifth of <hi>October</hi> 1087. He was a younger Son, but had the Crown bequeathed him by his Fathers Will: yet his elder Brother <hi>Robert</hi> endeavours by Arms to recover it from him, till <hi>William</hi> complied and consented to pay him three thousand Marks a year during his life, and leave him the Kingdom after his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease; which agreement put a period at present to their difference: and the said Duke <hi>Robert</hi> making an Expedition vvith <hi>Godfry</hi> of <hi>Bullen</hi> to <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to recover the <hi>Holy Land</hi> from Infidels, pawned his Dutchy of <hi>Normandy</hi> to his Brother King <hi>William</hi> for <hi>6666</hi> pounds, or as some vvrite, for twelve thousand and six hundred pound, which was so vast a sum in those dayes, that 'tis said, he laid a grievous Imposition, so that Bishops melted their Plate, and the Temporal Lords spoiled their Tenants to raise it.</p>
               <p>This King had Wars with <hi>Malcome</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:204203:15"/>King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and slew him and his El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest Son, which was so grievous to <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> his Wife, that she dyed for grief. This <hi>Margaret</hi> was a most Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Pious Lady, and the first that caused a barbarous custome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to be abrogated, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>when a man married, his Lord should lye the first night with his Bride;</hi> which Custom, by her endeavours, was altered to a Payment in money.</p>
               <p>He also made an absolute Conquest of <hi>Wales,</hi> and slew <hi>Rees</hi> the last <hi>Welch</hi> King. He built <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> and when 'twas finish'd found great fault because it was <hi>too little,</hi> and intended to have built one much larger. He was a Prince of great Courage, insomuch that being to cross the Sea into <hi>Normandy,</hi> to relieve his City of <hi>Nants,</hi> then besieged; the Sea-men being afraid to venture because of the tempestuous weather, he forc'd them to put out, saying, <hi>He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of any King that was drowned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Chamberlain having once bought him a pair of new Hose, he ask'd what they cost, and being told three shillings, began to storm, asking if he thought those of three shillings fit for a King to wear? Get thee gone (saith he) and let me have a pair of a Mark: His Chamberlain went, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204203:15"/>him another pair scarce so good as the former, and telling him they cost a Mark; I marry (saith the King) They are some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like: and was better satisfied with hearing what they <hi>cost,</hi> than with seeing what they were <hi>worth.</hi> More prudent was his Reply, when there being a rich Abbey vacant, two Monks came to him suing for the Place, offering great Sums, and each of them out-bidding another; Whereupon the King looking about, and spying another Monk standing not far off, ask'd him what he would give to be made Abbot of such a Place? who answering, he neither <hi>had any thing to give, nor would he give any thing if he had it.</hi> Well (said the King) thou hast spoken honestly, and <hi>deserv'st</hi> it better than either of these, and so gave it him for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>It was his common saying, That <hi>even God himself was obliged by his Word,</hi> and yet he himself was often observed not to keep his word. He is noted to have been very Covetous, and too much Irreligious, and some say very <hi>lascivious;</hi> which last may perhaps be the more excusable, because he was never married.</p>
               <p>He Reigned twelve years, and some odd months, and then being hunting in <hi>New
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204203:16"/>Forrest,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Tyrel</hi> his Bow-bearer shooting at a Deer, the Arrow glanced against a Tree, or as some say on the Back of the Deer, and flying forward hit the King on the Breast, whereof he instantly fell down dead, his body being drawn in a Colliers Cart with one Horse to <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> and there buried.</p>
               <p>In the fourth Year of his Reign, above sixty Houses in <hi>London</hi> were suddenly blown down by the Violence of the Wind, which was so great that it tore off the Roof of <hi>Bow</hi>-Church, and carried it a vast height in the Air; then letting them fall so furious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that six of the Beams almost Thirty Foot long a peice, were thereby driven twenty three Foot deep in the Ground, <hi>London</hi> Streets being then not paved. In his ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Year a Well at <hi>Finchampstead</hi> in <hi>Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire</hi> cast out Blood for many Days, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had done Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:204203:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>King Henry the First.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter this sudden Death of <hi>Rufus, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the younger Brother taking the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>Robert</hi>'s absence in the Wars at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> took upon him to succeed, of which 'tis said his Father the Conquerour prophesy'd when he gave him only a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, saying, <hi>Content thy self</hi> Harry, <hi>for the time will come, that thy turn shall be serv'd as well as theirs.</hi> However some time after <hi>Robert</hi> returns, and with a great Army lands at <hi>Portsmouth</hi> claiming the Crown, but Friends agreed the Business that <hi>Henry</hi> should pay three thousand Marks a Year as <hi>William</hi> had done before, and that <hi>Robert</hi> should enjoy the Kingdom if he survived.</p>
               <p>Two Years after, <hi>Robert</hi> coming over again for a Visit and being highly treated, Releases his three thousand Marks a Year, but after he was come home repents, and declares his Brother had cheated him, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Wars arise between them, and in Conclusion <hi>Robert</hi> is taken Prisoner, and shut up in <hi>Cardiff</hi>-Castle in <hi>Wales,</hi> having both his Eyes put out to prevent his Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204203:17"/>where he lamentably remained near thirty Years, and then died. The eldest Son of a Monarch, and who saw his two younger Brothers Kings, yet himself could never obtain a Crown. And 'tis obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that the English in this Battel with Duke <hi>Robert,</hi> did win <hi>Normandy</hi> the very same day fortieth Year that the <hi>Normans</hi> had Conquered <hi>England,</hi> which Dukedom of <hi>Normandy</hi> remain'd long after annext to the <hi>English</hi> Crown.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Henry</hi> was as great as ever his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Conquerour was, and married his Daughter <hi>Mawd</hi> to the Emperour. He made several wholesome Laws, and amongst others order'd, that Counterfeiters of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny should have their Eyes pull'd out, and their privy Members cut off. A Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as one judiciously observes) both <hi>less than Death and greater.</hi> In his time the Marriage of Priests being forbidden by a Canon, Cardinal <hi>John Cremensis</hi> was sent from the Pope about it, who in a Synod at <hi>London</hi> affirm'd their Marriage was no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Adultery, highly applauding <hi>Chastity</hi> and single Life, <hi>&amp;c. But was himself the very Night following taken in Bed with a Common Whore.</hi> More continent was <hi>Thomas</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>York,</hi> who about the same time
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204203:17"/>falling Sick, his Physitians told him nothing would do him good but to accompany with a Woman, who answer'd, the <hi>Remedy was worse than the Discase,</hi> and so resolutely perish a Virgin and perhaps one of Follies Martyrs. This King married <hi>Mawd,</hi> some Authors call her <hi>Matild,</hi> Sister to the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> famous for her Charity; for a Brother of hers coming to visit her one Morning, found her amidst a Company of Lame People, dressing their Ulcers and Sores, and then Kissing them when she had done, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he askt her how she could think the King would like to Kiss that Mouth which had Kissed such filthy People, to which she Answer'd, <hi>She had a greater King to Kiss, who She knew would like her never the worse for it.</hi> By this Saint King <hi>Henry</hi> had two Children, <hi>William</hi> drown'd at eighteen Years old (with many others coming out of <hi>France</hi>) and <hi>Mawd</hi> first married to the Emperour, and after his Death to <hi>Jeffery Plantaginet;</hi> to this Daughter he caused all the Bishops and Barones to swear Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but failed in his Design of her suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding him in the Throne.</p>
               <p>He was Counted very Learned in that Ignorant Age, and thence called Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarke; noted for a very temperate Prince,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204203:18"/>and yet he died by Intemperance, for, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting with eating a Lamprey he fell into a Fever, and died the first of <hi>December,</hi> 1135. Having rained thirty five Years and in the sixty seventh of his Age. His Bowels, Brains and Eyes were buried at <hi>Roan,</hi> the rest of his Body Stuffed with Salt and wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in Oxe-hides was brought over and Interr'd at <hi>Reading,</hi> being notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their Art most offensive all the Way, and his Brain so putrified as soon as he was dead, that the Chirurgion that opened the Head died with the noisome Stench thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>King</hi> Stephen.</head>
               <p>NO sooner was King <hi>Henry</hi> dead, but <hi>Stephen</hi> Son to the Earl of <hi>Blois</hi> by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dela</hi> Daughter to <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour snatches up the Crown, many of the Great men (notwithstanding both He and They had given their Oath to <hi>Mawd</hi> the Empress, King <hi>Henries</hi> Daughter and Heir,) joyning with him, which brought mighty Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles upon the Land, his whole Reign being but one continued Vexation; for at last,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204203:18"/>when he grew towards his last, we cannot say he was at quiet, being forc'd to make his Adversary his Heir, and leave his Crown to him that sought his Life, that is to say, <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, Son of this <hi>Mawd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His first Troubles were caused by <hi>David</hi> King of Scots, who being Uncle to <hi>Mawd,</hi> espoused her Quarrel, and entred <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi> with a potent Army, committing unheard of Cruelties, in ravishing Maids, murthering Infants and slaughtering Priests, even at the Altar; but at last were beaten back by several <hi>English</hi> Lords, eleven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>Scots</hi> being slain in one day; After this, several of the Nobility rebell'd against him, but were soon appeased; then <hi>Mawd</hi> came over in person to <hi>Arundel</hi>-Castle, and the City of <hi>Lincoln</hi> declaring for her, King <hi>Stephen</hi> besieges it, whither comes the Earl of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> base Brother to <hi>Mawd,</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; between whom was fought a bloody Battel, in which King <hi>Stephen</hi> (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had perform'd wonders for his own Valour) was at last taken Prisoner, and sent to <hi>Mawd</hi> the Empress, who kept him very rigorously in Fetters, and taking her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress to <hi>London,</hi> was generally received as Queen: Whereupon <hi>Matild Stephen's</hi> Wife petitions for her Husbands Liberty, desiring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204203:19"/>only that he might lead a private Life; which being rashly denied, she engages her Friends to raise new Forces, wherewith she gives the Empress Battel, and routing her Army, sets the King her Husband at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, who besieges <hi>Mawd</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi> so strictly, that she had no way to escape but by a stratagem; for it being a deep Snow, she arrayed her self and four Servants all in white, and so pass'd the Watches undisco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but in such a fright, that she never ventured her Person again in Action, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the War to her Son <hi>Henry,</hi> between whom and <hi>Stephen</hi> several Rencounters happen'd, till at last King <hi>Stephen's</hi> Son <hi>Eustace</hi> dying suddenly, he being thereby left Childless, was the more inclinable to a Peace, which was concluded upon terms, to hold the Kingdom during his Life, and then the said Prince <hi>Henry</hi> to succeed. From which time they lived as lovingly as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son; but it was not long e're <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> was taken with an Iliack Passion and the Hemorrhoids, and died at <hi>Dover</hi> the twenty fifth of <hi>October,</hi> 1154. when he had Reigned almost nineteen years, and lived nine and forty; being buried at <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:204203:19"/>
               <p> He was a Prince of great Strength and extraordinary Valour: and whereas <hi>Ralp</hi> the great Bishop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> had rais'd himself from a poor Priest in <hi>Normandy,</hi> to be Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England;</hi> this King on jealousie of his Loyalty, stript him of all his Preferments, and took from him forty thousand Marks which he had in money; in those dayes a vast and prodigious Sum. In this Kings time lived <hi>Johannes de Temporibus</hi> one of the Guard to <hi>Charlemain</hi> the Emperour, who lived three Hundred sixty and one Years. Also in his Dayes, there appeared two Children a Boy and a Girl, cloathed in Green, but of a Stuff unknown, of a strange Language and of a strange Diet, the Boy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed almost as soon as he was Baptised, but the Girl lived to be very old, and being askt from whence they came she answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they were of the Land of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> where there are Christian Churches erected, but that no Sun did ever rise unto them, but where that Land is, and how she came hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther she her self knew not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:204203:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the Second</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WAs Crowned at <hi>Westminster</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth of <hi>December</hi> 1155. Being a greater Prince than any of his Auncestours, and not inferior to any in <hi>Christendome</hi> in his time. For he had <hi>England, Normandy</hi> and <hi>Anjou</hi> in his own Right; and in the Right of his Wife, the Dutchy of <hi>Guyen</hi> and Earldom of <hi>Poictou:</hi> At his first coming to the Crown, he made Choice of Wise and Discreet Councellors, banisht Strangers, reformed Abuses of the Laws, and made many excellent Regulations to heal the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Politick of those Distempers and Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures which the late Wars had occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
               <p>He had married <hi>Eleanor</hi> late Wife to <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> the seventh of <hi>France,</hi> but by reason of their nearness of Blood from him divorced; with this <hi>Lewis</hi> he had some Differences ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up at last by a Peace, to render which more firm he matcht his eldest Son <hi>Henry</hi> not seven Years old to <hi>Margaret</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Kings Daughter scarce three.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:204203:20"/>
               <p> In the sixteenth Year of his Reign he Caused this <hi>Henry</hi> his Son to be Crowned King and reign with himself in his own time, who going back with his Queen to his Father-in-Law in <hi>France,</hi> he is there evilly perswaded to oppose his Father, and what was worse, his two Brothers <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Geoffry</hi> joyn in the Confederacy; nor was the King of <hi>Scots</hi> wanting to assist them, whence several bloody Battels in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Parts were fought between them, in which their Fathers Arms were generally blest with Success. At last a Reconciliation is made, and the <hi>French</hi> Kings other Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter betrothed to <hi>Richard</hi> the Second Son of the King of <hi>England,</hi> but afterwards his elder Brother <hi>Henry</hi> being dead, because that Marriage was not Solemniz'd and some fits of Jealousy, as if his Father were too kind to his intended Spouse, <hi>Richard</hi> falls again into discontent, and by the Aid of the <hi>French</hi> King took the City <hi>Mentz,</hi> forcing his Father to retreat. However, a Peace was clapt up between them shortly after.</p>
               <p>Besides these troubles with his Children, he had others almost as bad with <hi>Thomas Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et</hi> Arch-Bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who would by no means consent that Clergy-men who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204203:21"/>were Malefactors should be tried before the secular Magistrate as Lay men were; the Contention growing hot the King seizes on his Temporalities, and the Bishop excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated the King, and fled beyond Sea, at length he was admitted to return to his Office, but still persisting in his Insolence he was soon after by some Persons mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at Church, who was Canoniz'd for a Saint, and the King himself visited his Tomb, and suffered Penance there with a strange Humility, of which Saint some Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors report abundance of Miracles, but the greatest I observe is, that he was a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Pride.</p>
               <p>This King was the first that Conquered <hi>Ireland,</hi> and 'tis thought left in his Coffers at his Death nine hundred thousand Pounds, beside Plate and Jewels.</p>
               <p>In the twenty third Year of his Reign it rained Blood in the Isle of <hi>Wight</hi> two Hours together.</p>
               <p>He had five Sons, of which three lived to be Kings, <hi>viz. John</hi> crowned, and dying without Issue in his Life time, <hi>Richard</hi> who succeeded him, <hi>Geofry Plantaginet</hi> who dying in his Fathers Life time left a Son named <hi>Arthur;</hi> the fourth <hi>John,</hi> who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was King, and <hi>William</hi> who died
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204203:21"/>young. And of his three Daughters were Queens, <hi>Elenor</hi> married to <hi>Alphonse</hi> King of <hi>Castile,</hi> and <hi>Jane</hi> to <hi>William</hi> King of <hi>Sicily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He died, as 'tis suppos'd, of Grief, in the Year 1189. when he had lived sixty one Years, and Reigned near thirty five, being buried in <hi>France.</hi> This was that Prince that kept fair <hi>Rosamond</hi> in her Bower at <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stock,</hi> which enraging his Queen with Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy, she stirred up her Sons to Revenge her Injuries, and occasion'd most of his Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>King</hi> Richard <hi>the First.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Prince (for his valour Surnamed <hi>Coeur de Lion</hi> (or Lions-Heart) being Crowned the third of <hi>September</hi> 1189. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had settled his Realm, and provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a mighty Treasure besides what was left by his Father, resolves on an Expedition to the Holy Land, according to the Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Age, and sets forth with an Army of thirty thousand Foot, and five thousand Horse, having appointed to meet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204203:22"/>the <hi>French</hi> King in <hi>Sicily.</hi> In his passage being affronted by the People of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saults them, and subdues the Island, bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their King in Silver Fetters, thence he proceeds to <hi>Ptolomais</hi> which was soon fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred, and places a Garrison in the Town of <hi>Joppa,</hi> becoming very famous for his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in those Parts. Which being envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>French</hi> King, he pretends the Air did not agree with him, and obtains King <hi>Richard's</hi> Consent to return home, swearing first, not to molest his Territories in his absence, which Oath he not obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, King <hi>Richard</hi> was forc'd to quit his Glorious Design of winning <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> to defend his own Countries, but in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn privately for the greater Hast through <hi>Germany,</hi> by the Indiscretion of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Expences is discovered, and upon an old Grudg taken Prisoner by the Duke of <hi>Austria,</hi> where he was detained fifteen Months, till an Agreement was made for his Ransome at one hundred thousand Pounds, whereof fourscore thousand was paid down, the rest afterwards released.</p>
               <p>During his absence some disorders hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd at home, and some Mischief done by the <hi>French</hi> abroad; the first his Presence rectifyed, to redress the other he resolves
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204203:22"/>on Arms against that Kingdom, and being told as he was at Dinner, that King <hi>Phillip</hi> had besieged <hi>Vernoil,</hi> he swore he would not turn his Face till he was Revenged, and for Oath sake caused the Wall before him to be beaten down, that he might pass right forward, and speeds to <hi>Vernoil,</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> made as much hast to be gone, not without very great loss and more dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.</p>
               <p>In the Process of his Warrs besieging a Castle and unwarily approaching too near, he was wounded with a poison'd Arrow in the Arm, which enraged him so that he presently storm'd the Castle, and enquiring who it was shot him, one <hi>Bertrand</hi> own'd it, saying he did it in Revenge, because King <hi>Richard</hi> with his own hands had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly slain his Father and his Brethren; the King after some Pause gave him his Pardon and Liberty. An Art that shewed (saith a good Historian) <hi>that he had been at the Holy Land, or rather was going thither.</hi> For he died of that Wound, the sixth of <hi>April</hi> 1199, having Reigned nine Years and nine Months. In his Reign were found the Bones of <hi>Arthur</hi> the famous King of <hi>Britain,</hi> in the old Sepulchre at <hi>Glassen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi> And also there happened an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204203:23"/>Famine, followed by so great and general a Mortality that the living were scarce able to bury the dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The Reign of King</hi> John.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JOhn</hi> Brother of <hi>Richard,</hi> on Ascension-day 1199. took upon him the Crown; but <hi>Arthur</hi> the Son of his elder Brother <hi>Geofry Plantaginet,</hi> though absent in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Anjou,</hi> yet seeming to have a fairer Title, by the Aid of the King of <hi>France</hi> gave him much Trouble, till after several Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verses of War he took the said Prince <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> Prisoner, who soon after died, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drowned in the River <hi>Sein,</hi> attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make his Escape, as some relate, or made away as others suggest, is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               <p>After this, Discord arises between the King and several great Lords of the Land, on Pretence of Grievances, and to have the two famous Charters commonly called <hi>Magna Charta &amp; Charta de Foresta</hi> confirmed and observed, about which the Feuds grew to that height, that the Barons sent to <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:204203:23"/>King of <hi>France,</hi> requiring him to send over his Son <hi>Lewis</hi> to their Aid, promising they would submit themselves to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by him as their Sovereign; hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Lewis</hi> lands at <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and is receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there and at <hi>London,</hi> and Allegiance sworn to him by many of the Peers and Prelates. So that though there were no great Battel fought between King <hi>John</hi> and him, yet the Nation was miserably wasted by them, two Armies being a foot at once, each of them seeking to prey upon the other, and both upon the Country.</p>
               <p>But before things came to this Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a quarrel happens between the Pope, who had nominated <hi>Stephen Langton</hi> for Arch-Bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and King <hi>John</hi> who opposed him. The Pope hereupon threatned to excommunicate the King and Interdict the Kingdom, which at last he did, and the Realm remained under that Curse above six Years, during which time there was no publick Exercise of Religion, no Church open, no Sacraments admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred, Children went unbaptized, all that died were buried like Dogs in Ditches and Corners, but only such as had purchased or procured Licence from the Pope.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:204203:24"/>
               <p> But at last finding the Pope too hard for him, and the <hi>French</hi> King ready to invade him, King <hi>John</hi> is forced to submit, and taking off the Crown from his head laid it at the Feet of <hi>Pandulphus</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> Legate, who took it up and kept it three or four days before he restor'd it, all which time it might be truly said the Kingdom was without a King, as one <hi>Peter</hi> an <hi>Hermit</hi> had given out, that before such a day there should be no King in <hi>England;</hi> which though in some sort true during all that time, yet it being in some sort not true, and the King having a Prerogative of making his own Interpretation it cost both the poor <hi>Hermit</hi> and his Son their Lives for his Prophecy.</p>
               <p>Some time after, the King coming to <hi>Walpool</hi> in <hi>Norfolke</hi> (during the War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and Prince <hi>Lewis</hi>) and there losing all his Carriages, and a multitude of his men drowned in attempting to pass over, Anguish of mind cast him into a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whereof 'tis said he died, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers confidently relate, that he was poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son'd by a <hi>Monk</hi> of <hi>Swinesheads</hi> Abbey, who put the Poison of a Toad into a Cup of Wine, and to avoid Suspition drank first thereof himself, whereof they both imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately dyed the nineteenth of <hi>October</hi> 12 16,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204203:24"/>King <hi>John</hi> being aged fifty one Years, and having Reigned seventeen Years and six Months.</p>
               <p>He is noted to be somewhat Irreligiously disposed, for soon after he had made his Peace with the <hi>Pope,</hi> his Forces receiving a great overthrow in <hi>France,</hi> he said in a Rage, that <hi>nothing had prospered with him since the time he was reconcil'd to God and the Pope.</hi> Another time at the opening a fat Buck, see sayes he, <hi>how this Deer hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spered, and how fat he is, and yet I dare swear he never heard</hi> Mass. He squeez'd all sorts of his Subjects with severe Taxations, and invented strange Ways to get Money. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his time a Quarter of Wheat was usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally sold for twelve Pence, and a Quarter of Beans or Oats for a Groat, nor is the Price of Silver less altered, for then an Ounce was valued but twenty Pence, whereas now 'tis five Shillings, which seems a Riddle, for seeing Scarcity makes things dear, why should not Plenty make them cheaper, it being certain we have much more Silver now than then?</p>
               <p>In his dayes the Government of <hi>London</hi> by a Mayor and two Sherifs was first grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or at least not till then fully settled. A fist was taken in <hi>Suffolk</hi> exactly in shape
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204203:25"/>of a man, and kept six months on Land with raw Flesh and Fish, but then because they could not make it speak, they flung it into the Sea again. In <hi>Yorkshire</hi> there were seen five Moons at once, one in the East, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the West, a third in the North, a fourth in the South, and a fifth in the midst of the Element; and Hailstones are recorded to have fallen as big as Goose-Eggs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the Third.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOtwithstanding the Promises made to the <hi>French</hi> Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> after King <hi>John</hi>'s death, his Son <hi>Henry</hi> was Crowned King, chiefly by the means of <hi>William Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> who had married his Aunt, and (the young King being but nine Years old) was appointed Protector of the Realm during his Minority, who drew off divers of the Factious Lords; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing utterly defeated <hi>Lewises</hi> Forces at <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> and destroyed the Supplies sent him out of <hi>France</hi> in a Fight at Sea, obliged him to a Composition, for fifteen thousand Marks, renouncing not only all his Pretences
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204203:25"/>to <hi>England,</hi> but also swearing to restore when he came to be King all such Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>France</hi> as belong'd to this Crown; which he not performing, King <hi>Henry</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards made War upon him, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any notable success, Troubles encreas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home, because the King abandon'd his English Lords and trusted Strangers in his Councels and grand Offices: By which means he was grown into such extream Necessity for Money, that he coming to take up Money at Loan of a certain <hi>Abbot,</hi> told him, <hi>It was more Alms to give Mony to him, than to a Beggar that went from door to door.</hi> And yet, the Story says, the hard hearted <hi>Abbot</hi> would not lend him a Penny.</p>
               <p>He several times promised the Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the two great Charters of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Liberties, but yet still they were little regarded, one time especially they were confirm'd in the most solemn Manner that State or Religion could devise, a terrible Curse being pronounced against all that should break them.</p>
               <p>The Bishop of <hi>Bononia</hi> comes into <hi>England</hi> from the <hi>Pope,</hi> who pretending the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Sicily</hi> was at his Dispose, would needs bestow it upon <hi>Edmond</hi> the Kings
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204203:26"/>Son, sending a Ring to invest him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and King <hi>Henry</hi> takes it in so good Earnest, that he ever after calls his Son King of <hi>Sicily,</hi> but all this was done by the <hi>Pope</hi> only to bubble away the Kings Money, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn him into an engagement of an hundred and 50000 Marks for this kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, whereas he was so far from having Conquered that Kingdom, that <hi>Manfred</hi> Son of the Emperour <hi>Frederick</hi> had wholly routed his Holiness's Forces, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>established there.</p>
               <p>Contentions between the King and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons encreasing, a Parliament is held at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> called the <hi>Mad-Parliament,</hi> because ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things were Enacted against the Kings Prerogative, which proved after to the Confusion of the Realm and Death of many Noble-men; for their Acts not being obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, at last both Parties betake them to Arms, and near <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Sussex</hi> was fought a bloody Battel, wherein the Lords prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the King, with <hi>Richard</hi> his Brother King of the <hi>Romans</hi> and twenty five other Noble-men being taken, and of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons above twenty thousand slain. But Difference arising between the two great Heads of the Barons, <hi>Leicester</hi> and <hi>Glocester,</hi> the Latter joyns with the Prince escaped out
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204203:26"/>of Prison, and killing <hi>Leicester</hi> and routing his Forces set the King at Liberty.</p>
               <p>Both the Kings Sons <hi>Edward and Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> undertake the Holy-War, where the first carrying his wife <hi>Eleanor</hi> Daughter of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Spain</hi> along with him, he happened to be treacherously wounded in three Places by a <hi>Saracen</hi> with a poisoned knife, which by the Surgeons were judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and had proved Mortal, if she in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of Love had not with her Mouth suckt the Poison out of his Wounds, thereby ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting a Cure, which otherwise had been Incurable.</p>
               <p>During their absence, their Father in Peace after all his Troubles dyed, on the six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>November,</hi> 1272. having reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fifty six Years, leaving Sons, the said <hi>Edward</hi> who succeeded him, and <hi>Edmund</hi> created Earl of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> from whose Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the great Contention between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaster</hi> took beginning; and three Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters one married to the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the other to the Duke of <hi>Britain,</hi> the third died young.</p>
               <p>In the seventeenth year of his Reign was so great a Dearth, that People were constrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to eat Horse-Flesh and Barks of Trees, and in <hi>London</hi> twenty thousand were starv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204203:27"/>to Death for want of Food: and in his time was sent over from the <hi>French</hi> King the first Elephant that ever was seen in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> likewise <hi>Anno</hi> 1264. Five hundred <hi>Jews</hi> were slain in <hi>London,</hi> because one of them would have forced a Christian to have paid above two Pence Usury for the Loan of two Shillings for one Week.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. Edward <hi>the First, by Reason of his Tallness called</hi> Long-shank.</head>
               <p>THis Heroick Prince began his Reign in <hi>November</hi> 1272. But being absent in the Holy Land came not to <hi>England</hi> till above twelve Months afterwards, and then was joyfully Crowned. His first Attempt was to restrain the Exorbitance of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, by the Statute of Mortmain, forbidding the Encrease of their temporal Revenues <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His next Enterprize was against <hi>Leolyn</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> who rebelled against him, but was soon after slain, and his head Crowned with Ivy set upon the Tower of <hi>London.</hi> This was the last of the <hi>Welch</hi> Princes, in whose stead the Country being
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204203:27"/>wholly subdued, and King <hi>Edward</hi> having a Son born in those Territories <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>Caer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narvan,</hi> having caus'd ('tis said) his Queen to lye in there, on Purpose that they might have a Governour that was their Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, created him, <hi>viz. Edward</hi> that suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in the Crown, Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> whence the Title to this day belongs to the eldest Son of our Kings.</p>
               <p>And now grievous Wars arise with the <hi>Scots,</hi> whose King <hi>Alexander</hi> breaking his Neck by a Fall, and leaving no Issue, several Competitors, but especially <hi>John de Baliol</hi> and <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> pretended Title to the Crown, the Decision whereof was referred to King <hi>Edward</hi> as alledging a Right of Superiority over that Kingdom, who pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Crown on the Head of <hi>Baliol,</hi> he doing Homage for the same to himself. But afterwards confederating with <hi>France</hi> against King <hi>Edward,</hi> a mortal Dissention grew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; whereupon K. <hi>Edward</hi> marches towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> and wins <hi>Berwick</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the loss of the Lives of 20000 <hi>Scots,</hi> and takes <hi>Baliol</hi> Prisoner, leaving Officers there to manage that Realm, against whom <hi>Peter Walleys</hi> makes head, till <hi>Edward</hi> in a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Expedition at the Battel of <hi>Fonkirk</hi> kills above forty <hi>Scots,</hi> and seemed Master of the whole Land, the <hi>Scots</hi> swearing Feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204203:28"/>to him the third time, but to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, for then <hi>Bruce</hi> sets up for King, which so incensed King <hi>Edward,</hi> that he provides a mighty Army, and swears his Son and Nobles that if he died in that Expedition they should not bury his Corps, but carry it with them about <hi>Scotland,</hi> till they had vanquisht the Usurper, and absolutely brought the Country to Subjection, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his coming the Earl of Pembroke had put to flight the new King, with great slaughter at St. <hi>John</hi>'s Town, and our King had little to do but to cause Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be done on great Persons taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners, no Enemy daring to appear before, except that Invincible Enemy Death, who here seiz'd him with a Bloody Flux, and put an end to his Triumphs the seventh of <hi>July</hi> 1307. and thirty fifth Year of his Reign, having first (amongst other things) charged his Son on his Blessing never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call his old Companion in Extravagance <hi>Peirce Gaveston</hi> from Banishment, that he should carry his Bones about <hi>Scotland</hi> till he had subdued it, and send his Heart to the Holy Land, with thirty two thousand Pounds which he laid by for that Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:204203:28"/>
               <p> In this Kings time were all <hi>Jews</hi> banisht out of <hi>England,</hi> being above fifteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand, who had all their Goods confiscate, he likewise by Proclamation forbad the burning of Sea-coal in <hi>London</hi> and the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> for avoiding the noisome smoak. In his time <hi>Roger Bacon</hi> and <hi>Thomas Bungey,</hi> two learned Fryars, flourisht; who being great Mathematicians, were in that Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Age counted Conjurers, whence were raised the Fables of a Brasen Head, and walling <hi>England</hi> round with Brass <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the sixteenth Year of this King, as he and his Queen sate in their Chamber in <hi>Gascoin</hi> upon a Bed talking together, a thunder-Bolt came in at the Window, past between them, and shew two of their Gentlemen that stood behind them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>King</hi> Edward <hi>the Second.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe first Act this Degenerous Successor of a glorious Prince did, was to break his Fathers Will, by calling home his Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Gareston,</hi> on whom he bestowed most of the thirty thousand Pounds that was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204203:29"/>for the Holy War, and so little minded carrying the brave old Kings Bones about <hi>Scotland</hi> that it had been well he had suffer'd them quietly to be laid to rest in <hi>England,</hi> for after the Corps had been kept sixteen Weeks above Ground, and <hi>Langton</hi> the Treasurer and Executor of his Will was busie in preparing for the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, he caused him to be clapt up in Prison, and all his Goods given to <hi>Gareston,</hi> and then very indecently, before he perform'd his Fathers Funerals, enters into a Treaty of his own Nuptials with the Daughter of <hi>France,</hi> which were honour'd with the Presence of four Kings, <hi>viz. France, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varr,</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> and three Queens, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the old Queen of <hi>England,</hi> and Queen of <hi>Navarr,</hi> and yet <hi>Gareston</hi> exceeded them all in Bravery, who wholly possessing the Kings Affections the Lords caus'd him several times to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht, and the King as oft call'd him Home again: Insomuch that the Lords at last took Arms, and suprizing the said <hi>Gareston</hi> in <hi>Scarborough</hi>-Castle, cut off his Head, whose Body the King caused to be nobly buried, and built a Monastery on Purpose to pray for his Soul. He was the Son of an ordinary <hi>French</hi> Gentleman, of an
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204203:29"/>excellent Personage, and very witty, but exceeding debaucht.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>Bruce</hi> King of <hi>Scotland</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this King <hi>Edward</hi>'s easie Temper, takes Heart, and not only reduced all <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> but entred <hi>England,</hi> burning Towns <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At last King <hi>Edward</hi> raises an Army, but like himself, fitter for a Court than a Camp; many men and great Bravery, but no Souldiers; and accordingly they speed, for though his Army consisted of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand men, thirty thousand <hi>Scots</hi> routed them at the fatal Battel of <hi>Bannocks-Borough,</hi> and as Hector <hi>Boetius</hi> will have it kill'd fifty thousand of them; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards were Masters of the Land as farr as <hi>York:</hi> so that after several Disasters the King was forced to make Truce with them for fifteen Years.</p>
               <p>After this he becomes to dote on two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Favourites, one <hi>Spencer</hi> and his Father, as much as ever he did on <hi>Gareston.</hi> And much more mischief came of it; for the Lords striving to remove them by force, and being defeated, the Earl of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and above twenty of the greatest men in the Realm are put to Death. Then the Queen affronted by the said <hi>Spencer</hi> goes over into <hi>France</hi> with a Gallant, One <hi>Mortimer,</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204203:30"/>refusing to come back is banisht, but then like a true Woman she will come back, and to their Costs; for she comes with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, frights the King from <hi>London</hi> into <hi>Wales,</hi> where he is taken with his <hi>Spencers,</hi> Father and Son, which last are hang'd drawn and quarter'd, and himself that Winter kept Prisoner till Christmass, and then deposed, and made to resign his Crown, when he had Reign'd almost nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Years. He lived but half a Year after his Deposing, being by Means of the Queens pestilent Councellors hurried from Place to Place, in particular carrying him to <hi>Barkley-Castle:</hi> To the End he should not be known, they shaved his Head and Beard in a most insolent Manner, for taking him from his Horse, they set him on a Hillock, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king puddle-water out of the next Ditch went to wash him, telling him, cold Water must serve for this time, whereat the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable King looking sternly upon them, said he would <hi>have warm Water to wash him</hi> whether they would or no; and to make good his Word presently shed a <hi>shower of Tears.</hi> In the said Castle after several hardships he was by his inhumane Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers murdered, being first stifled in his Bed, and afterwards a red hot Iron thrust
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204203:30"/>thorow a Pipe up into his fundament, that it might not be discovered.</p>
               <p>In the eighth Year of his Reign was so terrible a Famine that Dogs and Horses were eaten, and Thieves in Prison pluckt such as were new brought in to pieces, and devour'd them half alive, which occasion'd such a Pestilence that the living were scarce able to bury the dead. And in his time digging the Foundation of a Work about <hi>Pauls,</hi> an hundred Heads of Oxen and Kine were found, which confirm'd the Opinion, that in the old time the same had been a Temple of <hi>Jupiter</hi> or <hi>Diana,</hi> where was Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Beasts. And then lived Sir <hi>John Mandevile</hi> the great Traveller, a Doctor in Physick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>King</hi> Edward <hi>the Third.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter the deposing of the Father, <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Son is proclaimed King, the seventeenth of <hi>January</hi> 1327. But being not above fifteen Years of Age, during his Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity Affairs were managed by the old Queen and her Friend <hi>Mortimer,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204203:31"/>a dishonourable Peace with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and a Match between <hi>David Bruce</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> King's Son, but seven Years old, and our Kings Sister, not so much. But in the third Year of his Reign the Queen by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is confined to a Castle, where she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd thirty Years, till her Death, with whom just ready to go to bed, was taken <hi>Mortimer</hi> by the King in Person, and several Lords, who being charged amongst other Crimes with being too familiar with the Queen, and betraying the Realm, was drawn to <hi>Tyburn</hi> and there hang'd up, his Body remaining an opprobrious Spectacle for all Beholders.</p>
               <p>About this time a Title to the Crown and Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> fell to this King <hi>Edward.</hi> For <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Issue, it came to him as being the Son of <hi>Isabel</hi> Sister to the said <hi>Charles,</hi> but they alleadging the Salick Law exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all Females, and such as claim under them from the Crown, set up <hi>Phillip Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois</hi> King, as being though more remote, yet descended of a Masculine Line, and King <hi>Edward</hi> had yet no Leisure to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it, being engaged in <hi>Scotland</hi> on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of young <hi>Baliol,</hi> with whom he joined to recover that Kingdom from the Usurper
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:204203:31"/>
                  <hi>David Bruce,</hi> though his Brother in Law; and in a Battel at <hi>Hallidown-Hill</hi> slow thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand <hi>Scots,</hi> establishing <hi>Baliol</hi> in the Throne upon <hi>Homage</hi> perform'd, all which time <hi>Bruce</hi> and his Wife remained in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having secured that troublesome and dangerous <hi>back Door,</hi> he takes upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the Title and Arms of King of <hi>France;</hi> and having destroy'd a Navy of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Ships that lay to hinder his Passage, and slain therein thirty thousand men, he entred <hi>France</hi> with an Army of fifty five thousand, and besieged <hi>Turnay,</hi> but a Truce was concluded for the present. However, about two Years after, King <hi>Edward</hi> goes again over with the <hi>black Prince</hi> his Son then but fifteen Years of Age, and takes <hi>Harfleur,</hi> the City of <hi>Caen,</hi> and divers other Cities, marching through the several Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces at his Pleasure, till having much weakned &amp; lessen'd the number of his men, being then above thirty thousand, the <hi>French</hi> King with an Army of above sixty thousand gives him Battel at <hi>Cressy,</hi> but is totally routed, having thirty thousand men slain, and King <hi>Phillip</hi> himself forc'd to fly in the Night to <hi>Bray,</hi> where the Guards asking, <hi>who goes there?</hi> He answered mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:204203:32"/>
                  <hi>the Fortune of</hi> France; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing known by his Voice was received into the Town with the Tears and Lamentations of his People, this memorable Victory was obtained on <hi>Bartholomew</hi> day 1346. And soon after, <hi>Calice</hi> is taken.</p>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Scots</hi> invaded <hi>England</hi> with an Army of sixty thousand, but by several Lords and the Queen in Person is routed at <hi>Nevils-Cross</hi> in the Bishoprick, fifteen thousand of his men slain, and he himself taken Prisoner and brought to <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phillip</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King dying, his Son <hi>John</hi> succeeds; and <hi>Edward</hi> the black Prince then grown up, having made great Hayock in <hi>France,</hi> at last happens the famous Battel of <hi>Poyctiers,</hi> the nineteenth of <hi>September</hi> 1357. The <hi>English</hi> were not above ten, some say but six thousand, and those weak and weary; but the <hi>French</hi> above three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score thousand, so that the Prince was content to have surrendred what Places he had got; but nothing would serve the <hi>French</hi> King, but he must, as vanquished, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himself and his Army to his Discretion; whereupon he rather chuses to fight him, which she did so successfully, that he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly defeated that vast Army, kill'd above
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204203:32"/>two thousand persons of Quality, and took King <hi>John</hi> himself and divers Lords Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who was brought over into <hi>England,</hi> to keep company with his Friend <hi>David</hi> King of Scotland, who both with King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> and the Prince, dined altogether at the Lord Mayors; and for this Victory, a Thanksgiving was appointed throughout all <hi>England</hi> for eight dayes together.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> King was afterwards Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somed for three Millions of Crowns of Gold, and the Black Prince goes into <hi>Spain,</hi> and with one Battel with thirty thousand against an hundred thousand men, puts <hi>Peter</hi> King of <hi>Castile</hi> into possession of his Kingdom, from whence he had been lately driven by the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Arragonians;</hi> but returning from thence dies, to the great grief of King <hi>Edward</hi> his Father, who not long after, <hi>viz.</hi> the 21 of <hi>June</hi> 1377. died himself, in the sixty fourth year of his Age, and two and fiftieth of his Reign. In his time happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a grievous Pestilence, which continued eight or nine years, and for some time so great, that in <hi>London</hi> between <hi>January</hi> and <hi>July</hi> died 57374 persons, and in <hi>Yarmouth</hi> in one year 7052. In the eleventh year of his Reign was so great a Plenty, that a Quarter of Wheat was sold for two shillings,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204203:33"/>a fat Ox for a Noble, a fat Sheep for six Pence, and a Pig for a Penny. He was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in <hi>Westminster</hi> Church, where the Sword he used in Battel is yet to be seen, being eight pound in weight, and seven foot long. In his time lived Sir <hi>Jeffery Chaucer,</hi> our <hi>English Homer,</hi> who happily turn'd the Groves of <hi>Woodstock</hi> into the Banks of <hi>Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</hi> This King left several Children, but especially <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> who married the sole Heir of the House of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> whose Issue <hi>Henry</hi> came to be King; and <hi>Edmund</hi> of <hi>Langley,</hi> afterwards created Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second.</head>
               <p>AFter the Death of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, <hi>Richard</hi> the Son of the Black Prince, being by his Grandfather in his Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time declared his Heir and rightful Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor, was Crowned <hi>July</hi> 16. 1377, being but eleven years old; Authority was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> his Uncles, with seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:204203:33"/>other Lords and Bishops to Manage the State.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>French</hi> hoping for an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by the Kings Minority, burn the Town of <hi>Rye,</hi> and land in the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and and offer Mischief at several other places, but are every where immediately repell'd with loss; as likewise the <hi>Scots</hi> were, who came on the same Errand. In his first Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>Alice Price,</hi> the late Kings Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress, was banish'd, and all her Goods (which were very considerable) confiscated. In the sixth year of his Reign, happened several great Insurrections, especially in <hi>Kent,</hi> where a Collector of Poll-money coming to the House of one <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> a Thatcher, and demanding a Groat for his Daughters head, her Mother alledged she was not of Age to pay; the rude fellow swore he would presently see that, and thereupon forcibly turn'd up her Coats; whereat the Mother making an out-cry, her husband, at work hard by, comes running, and with his Lathing-staff beat out the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors brains; and presently gathers a Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ripps up the ground of their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government, and by degrees encreased, and appeared at <hi>Black-heath</hi> near an hundred thousand strong; whence they march'd to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:204203:34"/>
                  <hi>London,</hi> cut off the heads of the Arch-bishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> and Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Hales</hi> Lord Treasurer, burn'd the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers Books and Writings in the Temple, and other mischiefs. At last <hi>William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> coming to <hi>Wat Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> at the head of his Rabble in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> kill'd him with his Dagger, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately the King comes riding up, crying out to the Commons, he would be their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and see all their Grievances redress'd, which, together with a power of armed men coming upon them, made them forthwith fling down their Weapons and beg for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, granted to all except <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> and some other Ring-leaders, who were execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For this Gallant Exploit <hi>Walworth</hi> was Knighted, and the Dagger added to the City Arms. The Design of these Rebels, as <hi>Straw</hi> declared at his death, was, to seize the King, destroy all the Nobles, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers and Clergy, except begging Fryars, whom they would keep to administer the Sacraments: to burn the City, take away the Custom of Bondmen, devise new Laws, and set up a King in each County <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> in the right of his Wife <hi>Constance</hi> Daughter of the King of <hi>Castile,</hi> pretends to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> and goes thither with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:204203:34"/>where, after several Adventures a Peace is concluded, on agreement that <hi>Henry</hi> the King of <hi>Spains</hi> eldest Son should marry <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharine</hi> the Dukes Daughter, and the Duke receive ten thousand Marks a year.</p>
               <p>Differences arise between King <hi>Richard</hi> and his Parliament, he demanding Money, and they wary in Granting any, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Favourites, and ill Ministers about him; insomuch that thirteen Lords were chosen by the Parliament to have the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight of Affairs under the King, but this the King soon after revokes; whereupon the Lords take Arms, and after some Treaties, come to <hi>London</hi> with an Army of forty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand men, and banish several Great men from the Court.</p>
               <p>After this a Parliament began (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Parliament that wrought won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,) the first day whereof all the Judges (but one) as they sat in their places, were Arrested; and sent to the Tower, and Sir <hi>Robert Tresilian</hi> Lord Chief Justice, not then appearing, was soon after found in an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries shop, and hanged at <hi>Tyburn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About his fifteenth year, on occasion of a Riot and some undutiful carriage, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the City of <hi>London</hi> were seized, and they at last forc'd to pay ten thousand
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204203:35"/>pounds to have them restored. In his twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year, the King goes over into <hi>France,</hi> and had an Interview with the <hi>French</hi> King, with extraordinary Magnificence, where a Peace was concluded, and King <hi>Richard</hi> married the Lady <hi>Isabel</hi> (not above eight years of Age) Daughter of the <hi>French</hi> King. 'Tis said this Journey cost him thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand Marks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bullingbrook,</hi> Son of <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and now Duke of <hi>Hereford,</hi> being banish'd, has tidings brought him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France,</hi> that his Father was dead, and that the King had seiz'd on all his Lands; Whereupon, aiming at the Crown, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing invited by a Faction, he comes back in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> pretending only to take posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of his Dukedom of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances descended to him from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which drew in many to assist him. King <hi>Richard</hi> was at that time absent in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who at length coming over too late, was taken at <hi>Flint</hi>-Castle, and finding the Faction resolved to depose him, did on the twenty ninth of <hi>September</hi> 1399. make a seeming voluntary Resignation of his Crown, desiring that his Cozen German the Duke of <hi>Lancaster</hi> might succeed. After which, he was conveyed to <hi>Leeds</hi>-Castle in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204203:35"/>
                  <hi>Kent,</hi> and thence to <hi>Pomfret,</hi> where he is said to have been murder'd by one Sir <hi>Piers</hi> of <hi>Exton,</hi> having Reigned twenty two years and three months.</p>
               <p>In his time <hi>John Wickliff</hi> opposed Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation, and other Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> In his fourteenth year, on <hi>Christmas</hi> day, a Dolphin was taken at <hi>London</hi> Bridge. In the last year of his Reign all the Bay-trees in <hi>England</hi> withered, and afterwards grew Green again; and a River near <hi>Bedford</hi> suddenly ceased its Course, so as the Channel remained dry for three miles space; which was adjudged to signifie the Revolt of his Subjects. In the beginning of his Reign, <hi>viz.</hi> about the year 1380. Guns were invented by a <hi>German</hi> Monk, who beating Brimstone in a Mortar, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with a Stone, a Spark happening to fall therein, blew up the stone; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon taking the hint from that observation, mixing the Ingredients, and putting them into a Pipe of Iron, he at last finisht the deadly Engine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:204203:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. Henry <hi>the Fourth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter the Resignation of King <hi>Richard, Henry</hi> of <hi>Lancaster</hi> assumes the Crown, as descended in a right Line from <hi>Henry</hi> the third his great Grandfather, yet, but from a second Son of that <hi>Henry,</hi> whereas there was living <hi>Roger</hi> Earl of <hi>March</hi> Son and Heir of <hi>Philippa,</hi> eldest Daughter and Heir to <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> one of the Sons of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, which <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> in a Parliament of the fourth Year of King <hi>Richard</hi> the second had been declared and proclaimed Heir Apparent to the Crown, but at present must submit, though his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily afterwards obtained the Royal Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth. And here began the Feuds betwixt the House of <hi>Lancaster</hi> or <hi>red Rose,</hi> whereof this King was the first, and the House of <hi>Clarence</hi> afterwards called the House of <hi>York</hi> or <hi>white Rose,</hi> (for by those Badges they were distinguished) which caused mighty Slaughters and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the Land, not quite appeased for near fourscore Years, <hi>viz.</hi> till they both became united by <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh, true
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204203:36"/>Heir of the <hi>Lancastrians,</hi> marrying <hi>Elizabeth</hi> eldest Daughter of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth true. Heir of the House of <hi>York.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the second Year of this King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Reign one <hi>Owen Glendour</hi> a <hi>Welch</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but educated in one of the Inns of Court at <hi>London,</hi> raised a Rebellion in <hi>Wales,</hi> and did much spoil, taking Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Lord <hi>Edmund Mortimer</hi> who resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. And some time after, the <hi>Pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> Earls of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Worcester,</hi> for releasing the said <hi>Mortimer</hi> their Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, enter into a Confederacy with the said <hi>Owen Glendour,</hi> (who was induced thereunto by a foolish Prophecy) to divide the Realm between them <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But King <hi>Henry</hi> fell upon them near <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> and kill'd six thousand of them, whereof 'tis said thirty six the King slew with his own hands, after which, <hi>Glendour</hi> fled into the Mountains, and being abandon'd of all, was famished in the Woods; a just End for such as upon the conceit of ridiculous pretended Prophecies, will venture into Rebellion. <hi>Anno</hi> 1404. The <hi>French</hi> made several attempts upon the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and other parts South and West, but were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually beaten off with Loss. About this time was a Parliament assembled at <hi>Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:204203:37"/>call'd <hi>Parliamentum Indoctum,</hi> or the Lay-mens Parliament, because the Sheriffs were commanded not to return any Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers for either Knights or Burgesses.</p>
               <p>The Kings Son, Prince <hi>Henry</hi> being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally valiant, and not yet full season'd, but drawn away with the wildness of Youth and ill Company, committed several Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagances; and in particular, one of his Companions being arraigned for Felony, he would by force have taken him away from the Kings Bench Bar, but being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood by the Lord Chief Justice, he stepped to him, and struck him over the face; whereat the Judge nothing daunted, rose up, and told him, that he did not this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to him, but to the King his Father, in whose place he sate; and therefore to make him know his fault, he commands him forthwith to be committed; The Prince, upon recollection, being smitten with his Grave and Majestick words, obey'd the Judges Sentence, and suffered himself to be led to Prison; which being presently told the King, he wonderfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced thereat, as well that he had a Judge of that Courage, as a Son of such Submission.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry,</hi> having freed himself from all his Troubles, makes great preparation for a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204203:37"/>Voyage to the Holy Land, though he were told by a South-sayer that he should dye in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> which proved nearer home than he imagined; for being at Prayers at St. <hi>Edwards</hi> Shrine, he was suddenly taken with an Apoplexy, and being carried into the Abbot of <hi>Westminster's</hi> house, when he recovered his Senses, finding himself in a strange place, he ask'd how they call'd it? and being told, in the Abbots house, in a Chamber call'd <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> Well then, says he, <hi>Lord have mercy on me,</hi> This is the <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> where I was told I should dye: which happen'd accordingly, <hi>March</hi> the twentieth 1413. when he had reigned thirteen years and an half. He was buried at <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the third year of his Reign, in <hi>March,</hi> appeared a Blazing Star, first betwixt the East and North, and then casting fiery beams towards the North. The same year, at <hi>Danbury</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> the Devil in the shape of a Gray Friar came into the Church, and put the People into great affrightment, the rather, for that at the same time there was a most violent tempest of Whirlwind and Thunder, that carried away the Steeple, and broke down half the Chancel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the fourth year of this King died the famous <hi>William Wickham,</hi> who from a poor, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204203:38"/>but small Scholar, came to be Bishop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> Lord Keeper, and abundance of other Preferments. He built New Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the Colledge at <hi>Winchester,</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged all the Prisoners throughout his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocese, that lay in Execution for debt under twenty pound; amended all the High ways from <hi>Winchester</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> on each side of the River, and divers other Noble Acts of Charity. The same year died <hi>Chaucer,</hi> and and five years after <hi>John Gower</hi> (who lies buried in St. <hi>Mary Overies Southwark</hi>) the two Fathers of <hi>English</hi> Poetry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the Fifth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> the fifth of that name, Son of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fourth, was Crowned on the ninth of <hi>April</hi> 1412. and with his Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his Nature seem'd wholly chang'd. Scarce shall we read of a more extravagant Prince, no where of a more brave, regular, and noble King; which he presently testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:204203:38"/>by sending for all his old wilde Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and giving them such competent Gifts as might maintain them in an honest and temperate course of Life; but withal strictly charged, that none of them should come within twenty miles of the Court, till they had given sufficient proof of the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Manners.</p>
               <p>He finding himself firmly settled on his Throne, began to revive the Title of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> which he solemnly demanded by his Ambassadours, but was scornfully answer'd; and 'tis said, the Dauphin (who in the <hi>French</hi> Kings sickness managed the State) sent him a Tun of Tennis-balls, in derision of his Youth, as fitter to play with them than to manage Arms; which so incensed King <hi>Henry,</hi> that he vow'd it should not be long e're he would toss such Iron Balls amongst them, that the best Arms in <hi>France</hi> should not be able to hold a Racket to return them. Accordingly he crossed the Sea with an Army, and landed in <hi>Normandy,</hi> where he took the strong Town of <hi>Harflew,</hi> and marching through <hi>Picardy,</hi> not having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove seven thousand men, was encountred by the <hi>French,</hi> being near threescore thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:204203:39"/>at a place call'd <hi>Agincourt;</hi> where, considering the number of his Enemies, and to avoid the fury of their Cavalry, he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged every Archer to take a sharp stake stud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Iron, about six foot long, and pitch them aslope before them, removeable by Pioneers, as there should be occasion; which being provided, and publick Prayers humbly made, he expected the Enemy, who about nine of clock in the morning with much pride and scorn attacqu'd him, but their horses being gall'd on the said stakes, were put into confusion, and thereby dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd the rest of their Army behind them, so that the Victory fell (with little loss) to the <hi>English,</hi> of whom were only slain the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who had the leading of the Van, and the Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> of persons of Note, and not above twenty six com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, as most Writers testifie; which may be counted (as Sir <hi>R. Baker</hi> observes) rather a Miracle than a Victory: for of the <hi>French</hi> there were slain above ten thousand. This Battel was fought the 25th of <hi>October,</hi> 1416. King <hi>Henry</hi> causing his whole Army in Array as they were to give God thanks, by singing that Psalm of <hi>David, When Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael went forth of Egypt,</hi> &amp;c. Proclamation being made that every one at the Words
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:204203:39"/>
                  <hi>Not unto us, O Lord, but to thy Name give the glory,</hi> should kneel down, and the Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bow their Bodies, &amp;c. And at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>London,</hi> shortly after, where he was Magnificently received, gave strict order that no Ballad or Song should be made or sung, more than of Thanksgiving to God for his Success, but without words of either dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing the <hi>French</hi> or extolling the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this time the Emperour <hi>Sigismund</hi> came over to give King <hi>Henry</hi> a Visit, who was nobly treated at Windsor, and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the order of the Garter. The <hi>French</hi> attempting to retake <hi>Harflew,</hi> and having blockt up the Mouth of the River <hi>Syne,</hi> with a great Navy, the Duke of <hi>Bedford</hi> went against them with a powerful Fleet, and destroyed in all five hundred Ships, and relieved the Town.</p>
               <p>On the twenty third of <hi>July,</hi> in the third Year of his Reign, King <hi>Henry</hi> went over again into <hi>France</hi> from <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> with an Army of 25528 fighting men, and a thousand Pioners, and took the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Caen,</hi> and <hi>Roan,</hi> and indeed went on victoriously at his Pleasure, till at last the <hi>French</hi> King sued for Peace, which up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Interview was concluded. King
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:204203:40"/>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> marrying the Lady <hi>Katharine,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King's Daughter, and being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Regent of <hi>France</hi> for the present, and Heir apparent to that Crown, which was confirmed by the three Estates of <hi>France</hi> in most Authentick manner. The Lords spiritual and temporal swearing to be obedient in all things to King <hi>Henry</hi> as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and after the Death of <hi>Charles</hi> should become his true Liege men and Subjects. After he and his new Queen had for some time been honourably treated at <hi>Paris,</hi> they came over, and she was Crowned at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> at which the King of <hi>Scots</hi> was present.</p>
               <p>Upon St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> day 1422. the Queen was delivered of a Son at <hi>Windsor</hi> (that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards succeeded to the Crown) of whom 'tis said, his Father, in a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Rapture, thus exprest himself, <hi>Good Lord! I Henry of</hi> Monmouth <hi>shall small time Reign and much get, and Henry of</hi> Windsor <hi>shall long time Reign and lose all, but Gods Will be done.</hi> Which proved true, for the Dauphin, who had never consented to the Peace with King <hi>Henry,</hi> besieging a Town called <hi>Cosney,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> went over to relieve it, but falling sick, some say of a Fever, others a Pleurisy, and some think
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:204203:40"/>poison'd, he died at <hi>Bois de Vincennes;</hi> whence his Body was conveyed in State to <hi>Paris,</hi> thence to <hi>Westminster,</hi> and there In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred, dying in the prime of his Age not above five or six and thirty, after he had Reigned nine Years and five Months, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Brother, the Duke of <hi>Bedford,</hi> Regent of <hi>France,</hi> and his Brother the Duke of <hi>Glocester</hi> (commonly called the good Duke) Protector of <hi>England,</hi> and of his Sons Persons, exhorting them to Unity between themselves, to be Loyal to their young King, assistant to his dear Queen, preserve what he had got, and never make Peace with the Dauphin untill he should absolutely submit.</p>
               <p>His Queen <hi>Katharine</hi> afterwards married <hi>Owen Teudor</hi> an Esquire of <hi>Wales</hi> of a most lovely Personage, by whom she had <hi>Edmund</hi> afterward Earl of <hi>Richmond,</hi> who marrying the sole Heir of <hi>John Beaufort</hi> Earl of <hi>Sommerset,</hi> was by her Father, unto King <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh the only Heir of the house of <hi>Lancaster.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this King's Reign Sir <hi>John Old-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle</hi> Lord <hi>Cobbam,</hi> favouring the Doctrine of <hi>Wicklife,</hi> was much troubled, and at last hang'd in a Chain by the middle in St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s Fields, and so consumed by Fire,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:204203:41"/>Gallowes and all; said to be for raising Sedition, though he were also convicted of Heresie, and thence 'tis like had a share in both Punishments.</p>
               <p>The Arch-Bishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod at <hi>Rochester</hi> made a Decree, that the Holy Scriptures ought not to be translated into the <hi>English</hi> Tongue, but 'tis recorded, that shortly after, his own Tongue swell'd so big towards the Root, that he could neither speak nor swallow, but in Horrour lay languishing till with Famine he dyed. In the fourth Year of this King's Reign was began the Council of Constance, where 'twas decreed that <hi>England</hi> should have the Title of the <hi>English</hi> Nation, and one of the five principal Nations of Christendome in Rank before <hi>Spain.</hi> At the same time <hi>John Huss</hi> and <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> were both burn'd there, notwithstanding the Emperour's Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Safe-conduct, and three Popes set up all at once, were all three put down, and a new legitimate Pope chosen, which had not been in the space of twenty nine Years before, so great is the Unity and fair the Succession which the <hi>Romanists</hi> boast of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:204203:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the Sixth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> the only Child of <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, being scarce nine months old succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Father, whose Infancy being assisted with good Protectors, his Affairs succeeded ed well, but afterwards began continually to decline, till at last he lost not only most of his Father's Conquests abroad, but even his Crown at home.</p>
               <p>His Regent in <hi>France</hi> was the Duke of <hi>Bedford,</hi> assisted by the two Terrors of the <hi>French, Thomas Montaeute</hi> Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord Talbot, who caused their young King to be proclaimed in <hi>Paris,</hi> and overthrew the Dauphin (who upon his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Death had likewise caused himself to be proclaimed King of <hi>France</hi>) in several Battels.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1431. King <hi>Henry</hi> not yet above nine Years old, being sent for over by the Duke of <hi>Bedford,</hi> was with great Solemnity Crowned King of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and received the Oaths of Homage and Fealty of all the <hi>French</hi> Nobility that were present and of all the Inhabitants of <hi>Paris,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:204203:42"/>and places adjacent. A little before this, a woman called commonly <hi>La Pucelle de Dieu, the Maid of God,</hi> pretended to be sent by Heaven to help the <hi>French,</hi> and expell the <hi>English,</hi> and marching along with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by her Counsel and Encouragement did the <hi>English</hi> much mischief, till at last she was taken by them, and being Judicial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned for a Sorceress, was publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burnt at <hi>Roan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on the fourteenth of <hi>September</hi> 1435, the wise and valiant Duke of <hi>Bedford</hi> died at <hi>Paris,</hi> with whom we may say in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner expired the good Fortune of the <hi>English</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> He was buried in a stately Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument at <hi>Roan,</hi> which some would after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards have had demolisht, as dishonourable to the <hi>French</hi> Nation; but King <hi>Lewis</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, <hi>"God forbid I should give way to so dishonourable an Act, as to disquiet his dead Bones who living would have disquieted us all: it savours of baseness to insult upon a dead Lion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Soon after this, <hi>Paris</hi> after having been seventeen Years in Possession of the <hi>English,</hi> revolts, and expells them, whose Example was followed by abundance of other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:204203:42"/>
               <p> 1441. One <hi>Margery Jordan</hi> called the Witch of <hi>Eye</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> was burnt in <hi>Smithfield;</hi> for endeavouring to destroy the King by Sorcery, making his Picture in Wax, which as it consumed so should his Body wast away.</p>
               <p>Then King <hi>Henry</hi> contrary to the advise of many of his Lords, marries the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> Neece to the <hi>French</hi> Queen, and Daughter to the Duke of <hi>Anjou;</hi> who sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himself King of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> but had only the Title, which Marriage causes many sad Inconveniences. For she and the Marquess of <hi>Suffolk</hi> (who made that Match) manage all things at their Pleasure, and procure the Kings Uncle the good Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> to be privately condemned for imaginary Crimes, and some say murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being found dead in his Bed; which indiscreet Act open'd a way to the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to pretend to the Crown, which he could not do during his Life, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended but from <hi>Edmund of Langly</hi> the fifth Son of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, whereas this Duke <hi>Humphery</hi> was descended from <hi>John a Gaunt</hi> the fourth Son; amongst other good Qualities, 'tis said he was well learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Astrology, whereof he wrote a speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Treatise intituled, <hi>Tabula Directionum.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:204203:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1450, the Duke of <hi>York</hi> begins se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly to cause disturbances. One <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> otherwise called <hi>Mortimer,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be his Cousin, styling himself Captain <hi>Mend-all,</hi> to redress Grievances, raised great Multitudes in <hi>Kent,</hi> with whom he marched into <hi>London,</hi> and passing <hi>London-Stone,</hi> struck his Sword therein, saying, <hi>Now is</hi> Mortimer <hi>Lord of this City;</hi> but taking too much liberty at last of plundering, after some dayes misrule, he was driven out, his Company dispersed, and himself taken in a Garden in <hi>Sussex,</hi> though not yielding till he was slain; whose Body being sent to <hi>London,</hi> his Head was set on the Bridge, and his Quarters at four several Towns in <hi>Kent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In 1455, the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> in hatred to the Duke of <hi>Somerset,</hi> joyns with <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and his brave Son the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> and others, who levy an Army, and fight the King at St. <hi>Albans,</hi> where <hi>Somerset</hi> is slain, and with him five thousand men; the King himself hurt in the Neck with an Arrow, flies to a poor thatcht house, where the Victorious Lords come to him on their knees, desiring pardon for what was past, since now the Common Enemy was slain; To which the good
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:204203:43"/>King, being affrighted, answered, <hi>Let there be no more killing then, and I will do what you will have me.</hi> Whereupon a Parliament is called, and the Duke of <hi>York</hi> made Protector of the Kings Person, and the Realm; but the Queen soon caused this Agreement to be countermanded, and after some time <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury</hi> is kill'd; the Duke of <hi>York</hi> retreats to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Warwick</hi> to <hi>Calice,</hi> of which he was Captain, and are all in Parliament attainted of Treason, and their Lands and Goods seized; But <hi>Warwick</hi> lands in <hi>Kent,</hi> gets the love of <hi>London,</hi> fights and routs the Kings Army near <hi>Northampton,</hi> and took his Majesty Prisoner; but the Queen and Prince fled into the North.</p>
               <p>And now in a Parliament 'tis agreed that <hi>Henry</hi> should be King for his Life, but <hi>Richard</hi> declared Heir apparent should suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. And if any of <hi>Henry</hi>'s Friends should attempt the disannulling this Act, then the Duke should have present possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Crown; But the Queen procures an Army in the North, whom the Duke of <hi>York</hi> meets at <hi>Wakefield,</hi> and there is slain with three thousand of his men; Then his Son <hi>Edward</hi> is left to finish the difficult work which he had cut out; first, he van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quishes part of the Kings Forces in the West,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:204203:44"/>then marches, (carrying King <hi>Henry</hi> with them) to fight the Queens Army at St. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans;</hi> but there they are worsted, and the King released by his Queen; but her Army being disorderly, <hi>London</hi> would not receive them, so that they were forced to retire. In the mean time the new Duke of <hi>York</hi> strengthens himself, and coming to <hi>London</hi> on the fourth of <hi>March</hi> 1460, is with great solemnity made King. And here all Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters agree to end the Reign of this King, though he lived twelve years after, and once more had the Sovereign Power, but it did not continue. He had now ruled thirty eight years, left one Son, who was after killed by Crook-back'd <hi>Richard,</hi> and so likewise was the Father himself, as we shall shortly acquaint you. In the thirty sixth year of his Reign it rained blood in <hi>Bedford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</hi> About this time the <hi>Turk</hi> took <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople</hi> from the <hi>Christians,</hi> which has ever since been the chief Seat of his Empire. And the Art of Printing found out at <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunce</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> was practised in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi>-Abbey by <hi>William Caxton</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Mercer; <hi>Anno</hi> 1471.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:204203:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>King</hi> Edward <hi>the Fourth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DUke <hi>Edward</hi> being acknowledg'd King, was not at leisure to attend the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of Coronation, but must once more fight for a Crown before he wears it. For King <hi>Henry</hi> had got together an Army in the North of threescore thousand, against whom King <hi>Edward</hi> marcht, having not forty thousand, and therefore being inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or in number, ordered no Quarter to be given; which occasion'd a mighty slaughter, there being slain that day six and thirty thousand seaven hundred threescore and sixteen Persons, whereby King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being totally routed, he with his Queen and Prince fled to the King of <hi>Scots</hi> for Aid, and soon after the Queen went on the same Errand into <hi>France;</hi> in the mean time <hi>Edward</hi> is triumphantly Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the twenty eighth of <hi>June</hi> 1461.</p>
               <p>Some time after King <hi>Henry</hi> (on what occasion is not known, unless led by the Ill hand of Destiny) venturing in disguise in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> is taken in <hi>Lincoln-shire,</hi> and brought Prisoner to the Tower of <hi>London;</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:204203:45"/>but is once more to be made the sport of treacherous Fortune. For King <hi>Edward</hi> sending his great Champion the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> into <hi>France</hi> to treat about a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage for him with the Lady <hi>Bona</hi> Sister to that Queen, who having proceeded far therein, the King in the mean time falls in Love with and marries the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Gray,</hi> Widdow of Sir <hi>John Gray</hi> of <hi>Groby.</hi> This odd Action so far disobliged the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> at his return, finding his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassy frustrated, the Lady <hi>Bona</hi> deluded, the <hi>French</hi> King deluded, and himself made the Instrument of all this; that he resolves to set up King <hi>Henry</hi> once again, whom he had before pull'd down; to which Purpose he confederates with the Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Brother, but at that time affronted; these raise Forces, and surprize King <hi>Edward</hi> in his Bed, near <hi>Berwick;</hi> but he soon makes shift to escape from them, and forces <hi>Warwick</hi> to fly the Land, but, being invited by the People, returns, and gathers so great a Strength, that King <hi>Edward,</hi> unable to resist it, is himself for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fly beyond Sea to the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the victorious Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leases King <hi>Henry</hi> from his Imprisonment
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:204203:45"/>in the Tower, where he had lain almost nine Years; and <hi>Edward</hi> is every where proclaim'd a Traitor, yet by and by assisted by the Duke of <hi>Burgoine,</hi> lands in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> declaring on Oath, that he came only to recover his own Inheritance; whereby the People thought he meant only his Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and therefore would not oppose him, whereas the sequel shew'd he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Crown. For the Duke of Clarence being reconciled to him, he marches for <hi>London (Warwick</hi> at <hi>Coventry</hi> being unable to fight him.) Here King <hi>Henry,</hi> who seem'd rather wholly passive than active in all these turmoils, is delivered into his hands; and the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> coming to <hi>Barnet</hi> is engaged by King <hi>Edward,</hi> and kill'd, but not without ten thousand Lives to accompany him. All this time Queen <hi>Margaret</hi> was detained by tempests in <hi>France,</hi> but when 'twas too late, landed at <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> but is defeated in <hi>Glocestershire,</hi> and taken, with her Son, who being bold in his Answers to King <hi>Edward</hi> was kill'd by crookback'd <hi>Richard,</hi> the King's Brother. Queen <hi>Margaret</hi> was afterwards ransom'd by her Father for great Sums of Money, and the pious but unfortunate King <hi>Henry,</hi> soon after this Overthrow of his Friends,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:204203:46"/>struck to the Heart with a Dagger by the said Crookback'd Duke of <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> being thus at Peace at home <hi>Anno</hi> 1474, goes over with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into <hi>France,</hi> demanding that Crown; but the Duke of <hi>Burgoine</hi> failing in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, a Peace was concluded, on Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the <hi>French</hi> King should pay fifty thousand Crowns a Year during the Life of King <hi>Edward;</hi> who on the nineteenth of <hi>April</hi> 1483, preparing for a second War with <hi>France</hi> for Non-payment of that Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, dyed at <hi>Westminster,</hi> leaving two Sons under age and several Daughters. He was one of the Goodliest Personages in the World, exceeding tall and majestical, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any man that married purely for Love, did so little love marriage says Sir <hi>Richard Baker; for he took as much Pleasure in other mens Wives as his own; being wont to say, that he had three Concubines that in their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Properties were excellent, one the merry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, another the subtilest, and the third the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Harlot in his Realm, as one whom no man could lightly get out of the Church to any place unless it were to his Bed.</hi> The merriest here intended was <hi>Jane Shore,</hi> a Cittizen's Wife, who afterwards died miserably.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:204203:46"/>
               <p> This King Reigned twenty two Years and one Moneth, in which time though there were wonderful Slaughters by Wars, yet two Pestilences happen'd that swept away more than the Sword.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>King</hi> Edward <hi>the Fifth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Prince was eleven Years old at his Fathers Death, but was never Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for being left to the Care of his Uncle the Crookback'd Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> and coming up towards <hi>London</hi> from <hi>Ludlow,</hi> where he then resided, the crafty Duke first made use of means to have the Guard at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his Nephew to be dismist, and then seizes on the Earl <hi>Rivers,</hi> his Uncle by the Mothers side, and other Kindred, whom soon after he beheaded.</p>
               <p>Having thus got the sole Custody of the King, the Queen-Mother fearing the worst, takes Sanctuary with her young Son the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and Daughters; but to get him from her, he pretends it necessary he should accompany the King to make him merry, and after much resistance prevails
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:204203:47"/>with the Queen to deliver him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they are both lodged in the Tower, and soon after by some vile Instrument al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged Bastardy against the Princes, and by the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> the said Duke of <hi>Glocester</hi> is proposed at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> as rightful Heir to the Crown, which he is solemnly intreated to accept, and after some hypocritical refusals, does take upon him, on the eighteenth of <hi>June</hi> 1483. two months and a few days after the Death of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth; the right Heir being kept with his Brother as Prisoners in the Tower, where shortly after they were cruelly murdered by one <hi>Miles Forrest,</hi> and <hi>James Dighton,</hi> Horse-keeper to Sir <hi>James Tyrrel.</hi> who stifled them with their Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nor was it known where they were burled, though 'tis thought part of their Bones were not long since found in a Wall in the Tower. This Sir <hi>James Tyrrel</hi> was afterwards beheaded for Treason, <hi>Forrest</hi> routed away peicemeal at St. <hi>Martins le Grand,</hi> and <hi>Dighton</hi> detested of all men dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed miserably at <hi>Calice.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:204203:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>King</hi> Richard <hi>the Third.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis cruel man having thus usurp'd the Crown, never enjoy'd it with any quiet of mind, but seem'd alwayes haunted with the Furies of Hell, and to bring him to destruction, some misunderstanding soon happens between him and his old friend the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> who being retired to his Castle of <hi>Brecknock,</hi> where, at that time, the Bishop of <hi>Ely</hi> (a discreet States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) was Prisoner, they laid a plot to put down King <hi>Richard,</hi> and bring in the Earl of <hi>Richmond,</hi> who was fled for safety to the Earl of <hi>Britain.</hi> This Earl, only Heir of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> they design to marry to the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> eldest Daughter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, and so <hi>Ʋnite</hi> the two Houses of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>York:</hi> But this contrivance was not carried so privately, but King <hi>Richard</hi> had an inkling of it, and the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> betrayed by one of his Servants, is beheaded; However, the Design still goes on. To frustrate which, King <hi>Richard,</hi> that scrupled nothing that might serve or secure his Ambition, uses means to marry the said
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:204203:48"/>Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and (strange to say) the Queen Dowager, her mother, is prevailed with to give her consent. Nay more, to smooth the way, King <hi>Richard's</hi> present Wife is suddenly sent out of the World, and now he resolves by a Rape on the young Lady, if fair means cannot effect it, to bring her to his Bed. But whilst these things are hatching, the Earl hastened by this news, arrived at <hi>Milford Haven,</hi> with not above 2000 men, but soon encreased by the coming in of the Country. To meet them King <hi>Richard,</hi> with what Forces he could, marches forwards, and at <hi>Bosworth</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire,</hi> on the twenty second of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust,</hi> 1485. the Armies Engaged, where King <hi>Richard</hi> desperately fighting was slain, his Body stript stark naked, thrown upon an Horse behind a Pursivant all besprinkled with Dirt and Mire, was brought to <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and there buried, and his Crown found amongst the spoil of the Field, set upon the Earls head, who succeeded, as by right of Inheritance was his due.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:204203:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the Seventh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe first considerable Act done by this King, was (according to his promise) to marry the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> thereby strengthening his Title to the Crown. Soon after happened the Sweating-sickness, whereby many thousands suddenly perish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the only Remedy was, assoon as a man was taken to lie down for the space of twenty four hours, not provoking Sweat, but letting the Disease have its course, eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or drinking not at all, or very mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Simmond</hi> a Priest having a Scholar call'd <hi>Lambert Symnel,</hi> of a pregnant Wit and comely Personage, he gives him out to be <hi>Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> Son of the Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> Brother to King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, lately escaped out of Prison; whereas, in truth, the said Earl was kept close in the Tower, getting with this Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>start into <hi>Ireland,</hi> he is there saluted King, assisted by the Dutchess of <hi>Burgoigne,</hi> who being of the House of <hi>York,</hi> bore a grudge to King <hi>Henry,</hi> as being of the House of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and countenanced by the Earl of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:204203:49"/>
                  <hi>Lincoln,</hi> who brought him over into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but near <hi>Newark</hi> upon <hi>Trent</hi> were routed, the Earl kill'd, and <hi>Symnel</hi> taken, who was preferred, instead of a Crown, to be a Turn-spit in the Kings Kitchin.</p>
               <p>Yet the Dutchess of <hi>Burgundy</hi> not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, sets up another counterfeit, one <hi>Perkin Warbeck,</hi> whom she breeds well, and instructs to take upon him the name of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> the younger Son of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, whom they pretended to have been spared in compassion to his youth, when his Brother was murdered. This Cheat not only deceived the <hi>Irish,</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> King believ'd it, or at least, seem'd to do so; as likewise the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> who in his quarrel entred <hi>England</hi> with a puissant Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but was repulsed; and upon making a Peace with King <hi>Henry,</hi> consents to banish <hi>Perkin,</hi> who afterwards making a distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> is taken, and put in the Tower; whence making an escape, being retaken, he was hang'd at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing his true Name and Parentage.</p>
               <p>In the 17 year of his Reign, his Son Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> married the Lady <hi>Katharine</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> he being of the age of fifteen, and she of eighteen years: At night they were put to bed, and lay together as man and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:204203:49"/>wife all night; when morning appeared, the Prince (as his servants reported) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for drink, which before he had not used to do; and being ask'd the cause, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer'd merrily, <hi>I have been too night in the midst of</hi> Spain, <hi>which is a hot Country, and that makes me so dry.</hi> But five months after he dyed, and Prince <hi>Henry</hi> (afterwards <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth) his Brother, by virtue of a Dispensation, married his Widow, as not having been carnally known by his Brother, though married to him. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Margaret,</hi> the Kings eldest Daughter, married the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in whose Royal Posterity both Kingdoms at last came to be united in the Person of King <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> towards the end of his Reign, grew intent upon getting of Wealth; for which purpose, two fit Instruments, both Barons of the Exchequer, offered themselves; <hi>Dudley,</hi> of a good Family, and <hi>Empson,</hi> the Son of a Sieve-maker, who turning Justice into Rapine and Extortion, by unusual summary proceedings, did much harass the People; for which, in the first year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, they were both behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and seven of their inferiour Agents, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Promoters, set on the Pillory in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:204203:50"/>with Papers on their heads, and then forc'd to ride through the City with their Faces to the Horse-tail, with the shame whereof, in seven dayes after, they all died in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry,</hi> in the twenty second year of his Reign, began to grow sickly, and afterwards died of a Ptisick at <hi>Richmond, April</hi> 22. 1508. and was magnificently bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at <hi>Westminster,</hi> when he had reigned twenty three years and eight months, and lived fifty two years.</p>
               <p>This King, in his eighteenth year, erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that sumptuous Building, call'd by the name of his Chapel to this day at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster:</hi> and 'tis reported, had in his Coffers at <hi>Richmond,</hi> under his own Key and keeping, eighteen hundred thousand pounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SUcceeded his Father, and was with much joy and solemnity Crowned. In the third Year of his Reign a War was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Parliament with <hi>France,</hi> for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:204203:50"/>our King's Inheritance, and the King of <hi>Spain</hi> promises Aid, but fails there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; so that little was done in the first Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition. But afterwards the King going in Person, besieges the City of <hi>Terwin,</hi> where the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> fought under his Banner, and received Wages, a hundred Crowns a day, an honour never done to any <hi>English</hi> King before. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Town with Victuals, came eight thousand brave <hi>French</hi> Horse, but were beat off by the <hi>English,</hi> and glad to fly so fast, that it was call'd <hi>the Battel of Spurs,</hi> as making more use of them in running away, than of their weapons in fighting: so that King <hi>Henry took</hi> the Place, and also the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Tourney.</hi> In the mean time the <hi>Scots</hi> invade <hi>England</hi> with an hundred thousand men, but by the Earl of <hi>Surrey</hi> at <hi>Flodden</hi> field are routed, and their King valiantly fighting, slain with above ten thousand of his People.</p>
               <p>In <hi>May</hi> 1514. the <hi>Pope</hi> being offended with the <hi>French</hi> King, transferred by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Lateran Council the Title of <hi>most Christian</hi> from him to King <hi>Henry,</hi> which with great solemnity was published at St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> but continued not long in use.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:204203:51"/>
               <p>1515, A Peace is concluded with <hi>France,</hi> the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Sister being married to the <hi>French</hi> King, who eighty two days after, dyes; whereupon the Lady is sent for back, and married to the Duke of <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> Woolsey, the Son of a Butcher of <hi>Ipswich,</hi> having by Learning and Diligence got to be King <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh's Chaplain, grew the grand Favourite of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, being made Arch-Bishop of <hi>York,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> by the King, and Cardinal by the <hi>Pope;</hi> who to honour his Brother Cardinal <hi>Campejus,</hi> coming hither from the <hi>Pope,</hi> sent store of red Cloth over to <hi>Callice,</hi> to make his Retinue fine, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him on <hi>Black-heath,</hi> in a Tent of Cloth of Gold; eight Mules he had laden with Necessaries, but <hi>Woolsey</hi> not thinking them enough, sent him twelve more; but see the shame of Pride! in <hi>Cheapside</hi> they overthrew their Coffers, whose Lids flying open, instead of rich Treasures discovered nothing but old ragged Cloths, broken Meat, marrow Bones, and Crusts of Bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the great Laughter of the People. This was that <hi>Woolsey</hi> whose Pride used to write <hi>I and my King,</hi> and falling into dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favour had all his vast Estate seized, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:204203:51"/>was arrested for Treason, and thereupon died for Grief; or, as some will suppose, poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned himself.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1522. King <hi>Henry</hi> for writing against <hi>Luther,</hi> by a Bull from <hi>Pope Adrian</hi> the sixth, had the Title of Defender of the Faith given him; the same Year a quarrel happens with <hi>France,</hi> but no extraordinary matters done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1528. Upon an overture of a Match between King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Daughter, the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Son to the <hi>French</hi> King, a question was started, whether the King's Marriage to the Lady <hi>Katharine,</hi> her mother, having been his Brother's Wife, were lawful or not? upon this (though some alleadg other Reasons) the King begins to declare his scruple, after twenty Years living together, the Opinions of the Universities abroad are desired, the King appoints Commissioners and the <hi>Pope</hi> sends a Legate to hear the Cause, from whom the Queen modestly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to the <hi>Pope;</hi> At whose delays the K. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offended, and at <hi>Woolsey,</hi> as some occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion thereof, first strips him of his Dignities, who thereupon dyes as you have heard, then casts off the <hi>Popes</hi> Jurisdiction, passes an Act that none should appeal to the See of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:204203:52"/>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> and takes upon himself the Title of <hi>Supream Head of the Church.</hi> Then in a Parliament his Marriage is dissolved, and decreed that she should no longer be called Queen, but Princess Dowager, after which time the King never saw her more, though she lived four Years.</p>
               <p>Soon after the King married <hi>Anne Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> and by her had <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> afterwards Queen, born <hi>Septemb.</hi> 7. 1534. between three and four a clock i'th' afternoon; but after she had been his Wife three years and three months, she was on a sudden seized with her Brother the Lord <hi>Rochford,</hi> and four of the Privy Chamber, were all behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: who on her Tryal, being charged with pretence of Adultery and Incest, she made such discreet modest Answers, as seemed to clear all she was charged with, and so did all the rest when they came to dye. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever she was condemned, and took her Death most patiently, desiring to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the King, and that they would tell him, His Majesty had been constant in his course of Advancing her, having from a private Gentlewoman made her a Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and from that a Queen; and now having left no higher degree of Worldly Honour, he would make her a Martyr. For
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:204203:52"/>indeed she was a very pious, vertuous Lady, and a Favourer of the Reformed Religion, which, together with the Kings affection to <hi>Jane Seymour,</hi> whom he married the very next day, were thought to be the only occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of her misfortune. For though the King had cast off the Popes Authority, yet he retained his Doctrine; so that great numbers on each side were put to death, Papists (as witty Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) for denying the Kings Supremacy, and Protestants for denying the real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, or holding that the Sacrament ought to be in both kinds, that Priests might mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that Monks Vows need not be kept, that private Masses were not useful, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular Confession necessary; which points were called the six Articles. By Queen <hi>Jane</hi> the King had Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> but she died in Child-bed of him. The Lord <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> being grown a great Favourite, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes the Reformation in some things, and all the Religious houses as they call'd them, that is, Abbeys, Fryeries and Nunneries, those Hives of Drones, were dissolved, whereby the King got vast Estates, yet in short time was never the Richer; though the Revenues of those Houses then seized amounted in the whole to 183707 <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>s. per Annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:204203:53"/>
               <p> Having continued a Widdow two Years, the King married <hi>Ann</hi> the Daughter of the Duke of <hi>Cleve,</hi> a Protestant Prince; but (as 'tis said) not liking her Person, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently displeased with <hi>Cromwel</hi> that made the Match, was divorced from her, and caused him to be apprehended, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted by Parliament; and without ever being call'd to answer (by a Law he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self had caused to be made) he was behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but for what is scarce known, only, the Record in general mentions, Heresy and Treason. He was a Smith's Son at <hi>Putney,</hi> and raised by <hi>Woolsey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About two Months after <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Cleves</hi> Divorce, the Lady <hi>Katharine Howard</hi> was openly shewed as Queen, and about a Year after was beheaded for scandalous living with one <hi>Deerham,</hi> whom she had formerly been contracted to, and with one <hi>Thomas Culpeper</hi> of the privy Chamber, who 'tis said both confest their Indictments, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being beheaded and the other hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>In his Thirty fourth Year he had Warrs with <hi>Scotland,</hi> where the Earl of <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> took <hi>Leith,</hi> and did other considerable Services.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:204203:53"/>
               <p> Next year, the King took for his sixth Wife, <hi>Katharine Parr</hi> the Widdow of the Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi> how she would have sped had he lived long, is not known; for, being a Protestant, she was accused of having Heretical Books, and a Warrant granted once for her Commitment; but pacifying the King with modest Excuses, she for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent escaped, he dying shortly after, and then she was married to <hi>Thomas Seymour</hi> Lord Admiral.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1545, the Earl of <hi>Lenox</hi> coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> the King received him kindly, and gave him in marriage the Lady <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> his, Sisters Daughter, by whom he had <hi>Henry,</hi> Father to King <hi>James.</hi> The same year King <hi>Henry</hi> in Person went into <hi>France,</hi> and took <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> and several other exploits were done by his Forces, but by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Emperour a Peace is Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>And now King <hi>Henry,</hi> grown extream fat, fell into a languishing Fever, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by Will appointed his Successor and Council, died on the twenty eighth of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 1547. in the fifty sixth Year of his Age, and thirty eighth of his Reign; leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Issue by Queen <hi>Jane,</hi> Prince <hi>Edward;</hi> by his first Wife <hi>Katharine</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:204203:54"/>Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> and by <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Bullen</hi> the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who all successively came to the Crown.</p>
               <p>In the fifteenth Year of his Reign divers things were newly brought into <hi>England,</hi> whereof was made this Rhyme.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Turkeys, Carps, Hopps, Piccarel and Beer,</l>
                  <l>Came first into <hi>England</hi> all in one Year.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In his thirty seaventh Year one <hi>William Foxley,</hi> a Potmaker for the Mint in the Tower, fell asleep, and could not with pinching or burning be awaked for full fourteen days, and then was in all respects as if he had slept but one Night, and lived fourty Years after. Nor could the Cause be found out, though he were examined strictly by the Kings Physicians, and the King himself. Now flourished the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men beyond Sea, as <hi>Vives, Erasmus, Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> &amp;c. and in <hi>England, John Collet</hi> Dean of <hi>Pauls,</hi> who founded that School, <hi>William Lilly</hi> first School-master there; whence our Grammar takes its name, though supposed to be composed by <hi>Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> and many others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:204203:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This Prince at nine Years old came to the Crown, the Earl of <hi>Hartford</hi> his Uncle being chosen Protector of the King and Kingdom during his Minority; his first Exploit is to invade <hi>Scotland,</hi> who refused to make good the Marriage between their young Queen and King <hi>Edward.</hi> This forces the <hi>Scots</hi> to carry the Fire-Cross throughout the Land, which was two Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands set in fashion of a Cross upon the point of a Spear, making Proclamation, that all between sixteen and sixty years of age should forthwith take Arms, and bring Victuals with them, on pain of death. By this means having rais'd a great Army, he Engag'd the <hi>English</hi> at <hi>Musselborough-field,</hi> but ten or twelve thousand of them being slain, and the rest routed, the Earl <hi>Huntley</hi> taken Prisoner, being ask'd how he was now inclined to the Marriage, very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somly repartee'd, <hi>He lik'd the Marriage well enough, but did not so well like that kind of wooing:</hi> And indeed all would not do, for the young Queen was privately convey'd
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:204203:55"/>into <hi>France,</hi> and being but six years old, married to the Dauphin.</p>
               <p>The two Popish Bishops, <hi>Bonner</hi> and <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner,</hi> are sent to the Tower, Images pull'd down, the use of Beads, Mass, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> restrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which occasion many stirrs and Insurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, especially in the West, but soon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peased, and many punished, by Sir <hi>William Kingston,</hi> the Provost-Marshal, who coming in shew as a Guest to the Mayor of <hi>Bodwin</hi> in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> desired him to erect a pair of Gallows for an Execution that was to be done there after dinner, which he causes to be done. Having dined with the Mayor at his house, they walk to see the Gallows, and the Marshal askt him, if he thought them strong enough? who answer'd, Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less they are. Then get you up speedily, says the other; for you have been a busie Rebel, and so forthwith hang'd him up. Near the same place, a Miller that had been concerned in the Tumults, fearing the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal, goes from home, bidding a man he had to say he was the Miller, if any body ask'd for him; which the fellow ignorantly does to the said Marshal, that came present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his Master was gone, but hearing order given for his hanging up on the next Tree, cryed out, he was not the Miller, but
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:204203:55"/>the Millers man; Nay, says the Marshal, I'le take you at your first word, <hi>If you are the Miller, you deserve it, or if you are his man you can never do him better service;</hi> and so truss'd him up.</p>
               <p>A fatal quarrel arises between the Lord Protector and his Brother the Lord Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, occasion'd by their Wives, the latter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving married the Queen Dowager, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Wife being a haughty woman, would not give her precedency, because her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was the elder Brother, and in higher Place. On this feud, she perswades the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector that the Admiral sought his Life, who thereupon was beheaded; and then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, being left without support, was soon supplanted by his Enemies, and charged with Treason, but on his submission releas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet not long afterwards, being call'd to a second account, when he had nobly acquitted himself of all Treason objected, he was found guilty of Felony on a Statute of his own procurement; That if any should attempt to kill a Privy Counsellor, though the Fact were never committed, it should be Felony; for which he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed on <hi>Tower-Hill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the sixth of <hi>July</hi> 1553. died King <hi>Edward</hi> at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> in the seventh year of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:204203:56"/>his Reign, and sixteenth of his Age. He was a most vertuous, hopeful Prince, of great Learning, for his time, and strict De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. Some say that he died of a Pleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risie, though some conceit he was poyson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Nosegay, it being generally mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured, after the two Uncles were taken out of the way, the Nephew would not long remain. Before he died, the Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> representing the obstinacy of his Sister <hi>Mary</hi> in Popery, and how fit it was Religion should be preserved in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which could not be, unless she were put by the Crown, nor that handsomly ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, unless the other Sister were put by also; on such reasons (nothing being so apt to take with the King as provision for Religion) he was perswaded by his Will (excluding both his Sisters) to appoint for his Successor the Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Mary</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighths younger Sister, which she had by the Duke of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> after the death of the <hi>French</hi> King, to whom she was first married; which Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> you must note, was lately married to the Lord <hi>Guilford,</hi> one of this Duke of <hi>Northumberlands</hi> Sons.</p>
               <p>This King <hi>Edward</hi> gave <hi>Christs</hi> Hospital for poor Children; for Lame and Diseased,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204203:56"/>St. <hi>Thomas's</hi> Hospital in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and St. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> by <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and for riotous idle Persons, his Palace of <hi>Bridewell,</hi> there to be kept at work by Correction. And in the fourth year of his Reign, Sir <hi>Andrew Jud,</hi> Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> founded a notable Free-School at <hi>Tunbridge</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> giving sixty pound <hi>per Annum</hi> Land to the <hi>Skinners</hi> Company, to pay twenty pound to the Master, and eight pound to the Usher there, and the rest to other Charitable uses.</p>
               <p>After his death the Lady <hi>Jane</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed Queen; but the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> being in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> takes upon her likewise the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and gathers Forces; against whom goes the Duke of <hi>Northumberland;</hi> but his men revolting, and thereupon the <hi>Londoners</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring for Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> he himself goes to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and proclaims her Queen, but for all that is taken Prisoner, and soon after beheaded; the Lady <hi>Jane</hi> being told by her Father, that now she must put off her Royal Robes, and be contented with a private Life, answered, <hi>She would more willingly put them off, than she put them on, which (she affirm'd) she had done meerly in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to him and her mother.</hi> And indeed, it proved fatal to them all, for both she, her Husband, and Father were condemned,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:204203:57"/>yet possibly had escaped with life being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieved. If the later had not afterwards joyned with <hi>Wiat</hi> in his Rebellion for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the Match with <hi>Spain,</hi> which enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Queen so, that not onely he lost his Head, but his Son the Lord <hi>Guilford</hi> too, who with much devotion and constancy submitted to the stroke of Death, which was given in the sight of his most excellent Spouse the Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> placed at a Window for that purpose; the object striking more terror to her heart, than the sight of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Ax by which she was presently to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: For as soon as he was dead she was brought on the same Scaffold, and after a most pious Prayer had her head severed from her body. She was but 16 years of age, but a Miracle for Learning, excellently skill'd in the Tongues, and some of her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles are yet extant. These qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made her much lamented, and the Judge that pronounced sentence against her, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently after fell raving mad, crying always <hi>Take away the Lady Jane, take her away from me;</hi> and so miserably ended his Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:204203:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. Queen <hi>Mary</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WAs crowned the first of <hi>October,</hi> 1553. and having settled her self against the Pretensions of the Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> as you have heard, and restored the Mass and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Religion in all Churches, of which she was ever zealous, as being of <hi>Spanish</hi> Bloud, and bred up with the Mother of Cardinal <hi>Pool,</hi> and other Zealots of that Party, she thought it time to marry being 37 years old; and at last <hi>Philip</hi> Prince of <hi>Spain,</hi> eld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Son to the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> is pitch'd upon and concluded; but some rash Spirits oppose it, of whom the chief was Sir <hi>Thomas Wiat</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> pretending that this Match tended to bring <hi>England</hi> under the Yoke of <hi>Spain,</hi> and make the Land a slave to stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Against him Forces were sent, but 500 revolted to him, who then boldly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched towards <hi>London,</hi> with so great terror to all people, that the Lawyers pleaded in <hi>Westminster Hall</hi> in Armour. The Queen by a loving Speech makes the City her Friend, who denied <hi>Wiat</hi> entrance; and his Army mouldring away, and being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compassed
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:204203:58"/>by the Queens Forces, who offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like a true Daughter of King <hi>Harry</hi> to have <hi>gone against him her self in person,</hi> he yielded up himself, and was beheaded and quartered.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the Princess <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being accounted a Protestant is kept as a Prisoner, sometimes in the Tower and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at <hi>Woodstock,</hi> and many Trains laid to ensnare her; to which purpose being questioned one day what she thought of the Real Presence, after some pause she thus dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly answered;
<q>
                     <l>Christ was the Word that spake it,</l>
                     <l>He took the Bread and brake it,</l>
                     <l>And what that Word did make it,</l>
                     <l>That I believe and take it.</l>
                  </q> Thereby avoiding their Net better than by a direct Answer she could have done.</p>
               <p>Three Bishops <hi>Cranmer, Ridley,</hi> and <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> are adjudged Hereticks, and burnt at <hi>Oxford;</hi> but before them <hi>Rogers, Hooper,</hi> and <hi>Bradford,</hi> suffered Martyrdom at <hi>London:</hi> and henceforward the Persecution continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very fierce during all her Reign.</p>
               <p>On the 20 <hi>July</hi> 1554. King <hi>Philip</hi> arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Southampton,</hi> and three days after
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:204203:58"/>they were married at <hi>Winchester;</hi> and short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after Cardinal <hi>Pool</hi> coming over, this Kingdom was absolv'd from what they then called Heresie and Schism, and restored to the Unity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. And the Queen in a fit of Devotion would needs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up all the Lands belonging to Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries that were in her own hands, to be disposed of as the Pope thought fit. And being told this would much lessen her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, answered, She more valued her Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than any Revenue. A Saying howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver grounded perhaps on a mistake as to particulars, yet certainly most pious and Christian in general.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1557. there was a piece of notable Justice: The Lord <hi>Sturton</hi> (though much in the Queens favour) being hanged at <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury</hi> with four of his Servants, for a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by them committed, all the favour he had being that the Halter was of Silk.</p>
               <p>The Queen engages in her Husbands quarrel against <hi>France,</hi> and took St. <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi> but for that there was little cause of joy, for many of the Garrison of <hi>Calis</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn out on that Service, the <hi>French</hi> took the opportunity to surprise it, and took the two best Sconces on a sudden, coming to the Walls the <hi>English</hi> had laid a Train
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:204203:59"/>of powder to blow them up; but their Cloths being wet by passing the Trenches dropping on it quench'd it, so that it would not take fire, so that the Town was taken for want of strength to defend it, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not above 700 Souldiers in it, after it had been in <hi>English</hi> hands 200 years. The loss of which, together with her Husbands absence, and the disappointment of proving not with Child, as she was generally report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, brought her into a sickness, whereof she died 17 <hi>Nov.</hi> 1558. having reigned 5 years and 4 moneths. Cardinal <hi>Pool</hi> dying the day before, some time before she declared to this effect, <hi>That if when she were dead they would look into her heart, they would find</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis <hi>her greatest distemper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her Reign is written in Histories with bloudy Characters, for the burning of poor Protestants, of whom in her time there suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered 5 Bishops, 21 Divines, and in all 277 persons.</p>
               <p>In her second year appeared in the Sky a Rainbow reversed, and two Suns at a time. Near <hi>Alborough</hi> in <hi>Suffolk</hi> on a Rock by the Sea, where there never was grass nor earth, in a dear year there grew naturally of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves such abundance of Pease, that the Poor gathered above 100 quarters.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:204203:59"/>
               <p> She died childless, and King <hi>Philip,</hi> as by Articles he was bound that he should not, so he was out of the Land, and could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing on the State; yet he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards sollicited Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the way of Marriage, (to whom before he had been very respective) but was put off by making an alteration in Religion, after which he never would prosecute his suit further.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>Queen</hi> Elizabeth.</head>
               <p>THis Virgin Princess, the Honour of our Nation, and Glory of her Sex, came to the Crown in the year 1558. and established the publick profession of the Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which as it made the Pope her mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal enemy, so the same with the refusal of his suit instigated the King of <hi>Spain</hi> against her. The Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> being married to the <hi>French</hi> King, and he soon after dying, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> could not but look upon her with a jealous Eye, and the Presbyterian Faction beginning to play <hi>Rex</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> driving out their said Queen, she came into
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:204203:60"/>
                  <hi>England</hi> in the Year 1568, for aid, where she was deteined eighteen Years and at last beheaded, an Action that Reason of State can never excuse, from being a Blot in the fair Reign of our otherwise matchless Queen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1569. A Rebellion broke out in the North, on pretence to have the <hi>Romish</hi> Religion reestablish'd, but was soon quash'd, some of the Inferiors hang'd, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the great ones fled the Realm.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> absolves all the Queens Subjects from their Allegiance, and curses all that obey her, by his Declaratory Bull, which in the Night was fastned upon the Bishop of <hi>London</hi>'s Palace Gates, by one <hi>John Felton,</hi> who never fled, but in an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected humour of Martyrdome, confess'd and justifyed the Fact, and was hang'd near the Place. If we consider the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s murder long after, and the manner of that <hi>Felton</hi>'s Carriage, one shall find some agreement in their extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as well as Names.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1571, Sir <hi>Thomas Gresham</hi> having finisht his Building in <hi>Corn-hil,</hi> for the use of Merchants, the Queen going to see it, caused an Herauld with sound of Trumpet to name it the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:204203:60"/>
               <p> In the nineteenth Year of her Reign at the Assizes at <hi>Oxford,</hi> as the Court was sitting, and one <hi>Jenks</hi> a Bookseller questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd for opprobrious Words against the Queen, they were suddenly surprized with a noisome Vapour, of which the Judg, Sheriff, divers Persons of Quality, and in all three hundred Persons died in fourty Hours.</p>
               <p>The poor distressed States of <hi>Holland,</hi> offer to the Queen the Sovereignty and Possession of those Countries, but she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused, only promised to mediate for them to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> for a safe Peace, but afterwards finding Don <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> plotting to deprive her of her Life and Crown, she did assist them with Men and Money, without which they had never been able to subsist.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Ireland</hi> there happen'd several Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions fomented by the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to quiet which cost the Queen great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Blood and Treasure, but they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ended with the overthrow of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</p>
               <p>On the 13 of <hi>November</hi> 1577. Captain <hi>Drake</hi> having before made several good Voiages to <hi>America,</hi> sets forth again with five Ships and a hundred sixty three Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:204203:61"/>for the Southern Sea, pafs'd the <hi>Stiaeghts</hi> of <hi>Magellan</hi> and at the Isle <hi>Moncha</hi> took out of a Spanish Ship four hundred pounds weight of Gold; in several places he found Ships with great quantities of Silver, and not a Porson in them, so inap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensive were the <hi>Spaniards</hi> then in that Coast, not fearing of any Enemy; after this he met with and took the <hi>Cacofago,</hi> a great <hi>Spanish</hi> Ship, and took out of her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides Jewels, fourscore pounds weight of Gold, thirteen Chests of Silver coyned, and a vast quantity of other Silver, and continued on his Voiage, till in three Years time he had sailed round about the World, his Ship being laid up for a Monument at <hi>Deptford,</hi> and he Knighted.</p>
               <p>About this time great means were used for a Marriage between the Queen and the Duke of <hi>Alanson,</hi> afterwards <hi>Anjou,</hi> brother to the <hi>French</hi> King, who came over into <hi>England,</hi> and was favourably received, but on a sudden the Match was broken off, and after many Years treaty came to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>And now passing over lesser matters comes on the Year 1688, wherein the <hi>Spanish</hi> Armado styled invincible, consisting of one hundred and thirty Sail, 19290
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:204203:61"/>Souldiers, 8350 Mariners, 2080 Gally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slaves, and 2630 great Ordnance, invaded <hi>England,</hi> having first received the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Blessing, who would needs have twelve of their best Ships called by the respective names of the twelve Apostles. This Navy was to bring over the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi>'s Army, being fifty thousand old Souldiers, out of <hi>Flanders;</hi> but whilst they were wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him, the Queen having by a Camp at <hi>Tilbury,</hi> twenty thousand men, laid on the Sea Coast, and a brave Army for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of her Person; secured the Land, set forth her Navy under the Lord <hi>Howard</hi> Admiral, and <hi>Drake</hi> Vice-Admiral, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter several Engagements and the Stratagem of Fire-ships, (then first used) utterly disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed that vast Navy, above half their Ships being taken, destroyed, or lost, and the rest forced to fly round the North of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to get home. A Victory never to be forgot by either <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> for it's contrary Influence on their Affairs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1594, <hi>Lopez</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> Physitian to the Queen, was executed for attempting to poison her. In 1600. the Earl of <hi>Essez</hi> having incurr'd the Queens Displeasure in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and more by scandalous Speeches, and a kind of open Rebellion at his House
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204203:62"/>in <hi>London,</hi> being condemned by his Peers is beheaded. On the 24th. of <hi>March,</hi> or last day of the year 1602. died Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> having reigned above 44 years in as troublesom times as any, yet full of Honour, and most happy in the Love of her People.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>King</hi> James.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JAmes</hi> the Sixth King of <hi>Scotland</hi> of that Name, being descended from <hi>Margaret</hi> the eldest daughter of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, had after Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> death an undoubted Right to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and was accordingly proclaimed the very last day of the year 1602. and in <hi>May</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing arrived in <hi>London,</hi> but was not crowned till a pretty while afterwards.</p>
               <p>In the third year of his Reign was the horrid Gunpowder Treason, a Plot laid by <hi>Henry Garnet</hi> a Jesuit, <hi>Robert Catesby, Thomas Piercy, Thomas Winter, Guido Fawks,</hi> and other desperate Papists, to blow up both Houses of Parliament, King, Prince, Lords, and Commons, all together; to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose having taken an oath of Secrecy, and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:204203:62"/>hired an House adjoyning, they began to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine, but at last heard of a Cellar right under the Parliament House, to be let; which they hire and stow their Powder in, covered over to prevent suspicion with Billets and Faggots, the day appointed for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments meeting, and consequently this Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution was the Fifth of <hi>November;</hi> but 10 days before, a stranger delivers a Letter to the Lord <hi>Mounteagles</hi> Man to give to his Lord, the words whereof were these.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>OƲt of the love I bear to some of your friends, I have a care of your preservation; therefore I would wish you as you tender your life to forbear your attendance at this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for God and Man have concurred to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the wickedness of this time. And think not slight of this Advertisement, but retire your self into your Country, where you may expect the event in safety. For though there be no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of any stir, yet I say they shall receive a terrible blow this Parliament, and yet shall not see who hurts them. This counsel is not to be contemned, and can do you no harm, for the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is past so soon as you have burnt this Letter; and I hope God will give you grace to make good use of it, to whose holy protection I commend you.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:204203:63"/>
               <p> Indeed God did give my Lord grace to make the best use of it, which was to shew it to the King and Council; but being in a counterfeit imperfect hand, without Name or Date, they knew not what to make of it, till His Majesty by that word <hi>terrible blow, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>the danger will be over as soon as you have burnt this Letter,</hi> did most sagaciously conjecture it might be mischief by blowing up with Gunpowder, and ordered privy search to be made, where the very night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Parliament was to meet, coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the said Cellar, and removing the Billets, they found first one, and then the rest, in all 36 Barrels of Powder, and took <hi>Fawks</hi> standing suspiciously in the Entry, and in his pocket a piece of Touch-wood, a Tinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>box, a Match, &amp;c. The rest were gone down into the Country, on pretence of a Hunting Match to raise Rebellion, and seize the Duke of <hi>York</hi> and Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which last then lying in <hi>Warwick-shire,</hi> they intended to proclaim Queen, and rule all things at their pleasure.</p>
               <p>But now after some resistance, wherein <hi>Catesby</hi> and <hi>Piercy</hi> fighting back to back, were both killed with one Musquet-shot, and some others slain. The rest were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:204203:63"/>hang'd, drawn, and quartered; and the day ordered to be celebrated to all Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Next year <hi>Christianus</hi> King of <hi>Denmark</hi> Queen <hi>Anns</hi> Brother came into <hi>England,</hi> and after a moneths magnificent Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment returned.</p>
               <p>In the year 1610. Prince <hi>Henry</hi> aged 17 years was created Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> with great solemnity, but 2 years after falling sick of a malignant Fever he died on the sixth of <hi>November</hi> 1612. who being a Prince of extraordinary hopes, and infinitely beloved of the people, his death caused a general sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and eclipsed the joys of the Marriage between the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and Prince <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> which just at that time was solemnized.</p>
               <p>About this time <hi>Hugh Middleton,</hi> Citizen and Goldsmith of <hi>London,</hi> with vast cost and labour brought the New River water to that City: and to add to the beauty of the Town near the same time <hi>Meorfields,</hi> which was nothing but dirty heaps and noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som common shores, was made sweet and clean, and distinguished into Walks, and set with Trees, and <hi>Smithfield</hi> first of all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:204203:64"/>
               <p> 1617. Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> condemned for Treason upon King <hi>James</hi> first coming in, after 15 years imprisonment in the Tower, where he wrote the History of the World, got leave to go to <hi>Guyana,</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he knew of a Gold Mine there, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not succesful therein, <hi>Gondomor</hi> the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> Ambassador made such Complaints, that upon his former judgment he was beheaded in the Palace-Yard at <hi>Westminster;</hi> a man both for a Souldier, a Seaman, and a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, scarce to be match'd in this later age.</p>
               <p>1619. Queen <hi>Ann</hi> died, and about a year after, the Count Palatine having thus mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Daughter of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> was thought fit to be King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and elected by the States, but was no sooner crowned, but the Emperour with great Forces fell upon him, which occasion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much trouble afterwards to that. Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Family.</p>
               <p>A Match is proposed for Prince <hi>Charles</hi> with the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> who to speed it on undertakes a journey thither in person, travelling privately through <hi>France,</hi> where by chance he had a sight of that incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lady that was afterwards his Queen; for no good being to be done in <hi>Spain,</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with delays, he returns and enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:204203:64"/>a Treaty with <hi>France,</hi> during which King <hi>James</hi> died of an Ague at <hi>Theobalds, March</hi> 27. 1625, having reigned 22 years, and in the 59th. of his age. A Prince justly styled the Peace-maker, and for his Learning, Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Plenty of his Reign celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as our <hi>English Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the first year of his Reign happened a great Plague, of which in one year 30244 persons died in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his second year one <hi>Ann Waters</hi> enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by a Lover of hers, consented to have her Husband strangled, and buried under the Dunghil in the Cow-house. The man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing missing and she pretending to wonder what was become of him, a Neighbour hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to dream that the said <hi>Waters</hi> was strangled and buried in such a place, who declaring his dream, a search is made, the body found, the Wife examined, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing was burnt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1609. A Fire began in a Mault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house in <hi>Saint Edmondsbury,</hi> and consumed 160 Houses, towards rebuilding whereof the King gave 500 loads of Timber.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1618. In <hi>November</hi> was the great Comet seen, after which followed the Wars in <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:204203:65"/>
               <p> On Friday <hi>October</hi> 24. 1623. At the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Conventicle in <hi>Black Friars</hi> by the fall of the Floor, the Priest, and almost 100 of his Auditors were killed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1606. The King first granted a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to <hi>London</hi> for a Plantation in <hi>Virginia,</hi> and another to <hi>Bristoll, Exeter,</hi> and <hi>Plimouth,</hi> for a Plantation in <hi>New England,</hi> which then began to be peopled with <hi>English.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the First</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEgan his Reign 27 <hi>March</hi> 1625, and in <hi>June</hi> following was married to <hi>Henrietta Maria,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great.</p>
               <p>In the year 1627. was the unfortunate Expedition to the Isle of <hi>Rhe,</hi> designed for the assistance of the <hi>French</hi> Protestants in <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> and the next year a second attempt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; but the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for it at <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> was assassinated by the barbarous hands of <hi>John Felton,</hi> who for that horrid Murther was first hanged at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> and his body exposed in Chains at <hi>Portsmouth.</hi> Upon the noble Duke was made this Epitaph by one of the Celebrated Wits of that Age.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:204203:65"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here lies the best and worst of Fate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Two Kings Delight, but Factions Hate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Courtiers Star, the Kingdoms Eye,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Man to draw an Angel by,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fears Despiser, great</hi> Villiers <hi>Glory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Great mans Volum, All times Story.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Nor did <hi>Felton</hi> want an Epitaph, but had the following Lines bestowed on him, by a Pen whose exquisite Fancy deserved a more happy subject.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>An Epitaph on <hi>John Felton,</hi> that stabb'd the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> at <hi>Portsmouth, Anno 1621.</hi> and was there hang'd in Chains.</head>
                  <l>Here <hi>uninterr'd</hi> suspends (though not to save</l>
                  <l>Surviving <hi>Friends</hi> th'expences of a Grave)</l>
                  <l>Feltons <hi>dead earth,</hi> which to the world must be</l>
                  <l>Its own sad <hi>Monument,</hi> his <hi>Elegy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As large as Fame; but whether <hi>bad</hi> or <hi>good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I say not; By himself 'twas wrote in <hi>Bloud.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For which his body is <hi>entomb'd</hi> in Air,</l>
                  <l>Arch'd o're with <hi>Heav'n,</hi> set with a Thousand fair</l>
                  <l>And glorious <hi>Stars,</hi> a noble Sepulcher,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Time</hi> it self can't ruinate, and where</l>
                  <l>Th' Impartial <hi>Worm,</hi> that is not brib'd to spare</l>
                  <l>Princes (<hi>Corrupt</hi> in Marble) cannot share.</l>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:204203:66"/>
                  <l>His <hi>Flesh</hi> (which oft the charitable Skies</l>
                  <l>Embalm with <hi>Tears,</hi> deigning those Obsequies</l>
                  <l>Belong to Men) shall <hi>last</hi> till pitying <hi>Fowl</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Contend to <hi>reach</hi> his <hi>Body</hi> to his <hi>Soul.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>The 29th of <hi>May</hi> 1630, was born <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d, our present Sovereign, a Star appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the same time at Noon-day, as an Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious presage of the peculiar care Heaven would take of that Royal Native.</p>
               <p>In the year 1639. the <hi>Scots,</hi> stirred up and influenced by certain Presbyterian Factious Spirits, begin a Rebellion, and march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>England,</hi> whom the King meets with a strong Army. A Pacification is made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; yet the next year they come on again, encouraged by a treacherous Party here, and a Treaty being had, a Truce is made with them.</p>
               <p>The 3d. of <hi>November</hi> 1640. began that fatal Parliament, terribly known by the Name of the <hi>Long;</hi> and now the ill Weeds of Rebellion grow so fast, that we must one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hint at the time of principal Actions, without running out into Circumstances.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Wednesday</hi> the 12th of <hi>May</hi> 1641, that prudent and loyal Statesman <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> was taken off by a popular fury, and noise of an Accumulative Treason, though
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:204203:66"/>nothing Criminal was proved against him: But his Loyalty was to them Crime enough, and even themselves seemed to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his Innocence, since they thought fit to fling away the Helve of that Hatchet wherewith they cut off his head, by Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Case should never be drawn into President.</p>
               <p>In <hi>August</hi> following the King goes into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and is received with extraordinary joy at his Return. During his absence, <hi>viz.</hi> on the 23. of <hi>October</hi> breaks out the horrid Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and here at home Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults increase with such insolence, that the King finds himself obliged to retire for his safety from <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and having used all means that a most loving and pious Prince could condescend to, to bring the Faction to moderation and a sense of their duty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing denied entrance into his Town of <hi>Hull,</hi> and seeing his Right of the <hi>Militia</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to be invaded, &amp;c. resolves to defend himself, and the Liberties of his People, by gathering what strength he could, setting up his Standard at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> 24 <hi>August,</hi> 1642. as on the contrary the Parliament form an Army under Command of the Earl of <hi>Essex.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:204203:67"/>
               <p> The first considerable Battel was at <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> 23 <hi>October</hi> 1642. wherein His Majesty had so much the better, that he kept possession of the Field.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brainford</hi> Fight, 12 <hi>November</hi> 1642.</p>
               <p>The Battel at <hi>Hopton Heath, March</hi> 19. 1642.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Newbury</hi> first Fight 20 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1643.</p>
               <p>The terrible Battel at <hi>Maston Moor</hi> near <hi>York,</hi> wherein the Kings Forces were at last worsted, and several persons of note slain, <hi>July</hi> 2, 1644.</p>
               <p>The Parliament Forces in <hi>Cornwall</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to submit, and their <hi>General Essex</hi> to fly away by Sea, <hi>Sept.</hi> 1644.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Newbury</hi> second Fight 27 <hi>Oct.</hi> 1644.</p>
               <p>Treaty at <hi>Ʋxbridge</hi> began 30 <hi>January,</hi> 1644.</p>
               <p>The Battel at <hi>Naseby</hi> fatal to the Royal Interest, 14 <hi>June</hi> 1645.</p>
               <p>27 <hi>April</hi> 1646. the Kings Majesty is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced privately to depart from <hi>Oxford,</hi> and went to the <hi>Scotish</hi> Army, who afterwards consent to surrender his person to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Rebels; whereupon after several Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verses of Fortune he is brought to <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> 28 <hi>Aug.</hi> 1648.</p>
               <p>The King being now in restraint, many of his Subjects that had before been misled
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:204203:67"/>to take Arms against him, begin to look upon his Estate with Commiseration. A great part of the Navy revolt to the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> several Towns and Castles, and particularly that of <hi>Pomfret</hi> was surprized for his Majesties Service, the Duke of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> with Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale</hi> and others raise a strong Army for the King in the North, and the <hi>Kentishmen</hi> in great numbers are up in Arms under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Goring</hi> Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> so that a general Tempest seem'd to threaten the Parliaments Affairs, but was all soon blown over. For <hi>Cromwel</hi> then Lieutenant, quickly reduces the <hi>Welch,</hi> where <hi>Langhorn, Poyer,</hi> and <hi>Powel</hi> their Captains are executed: then marching against those of the <hi>North,</hi> he meets them in <hi>Lancashire,</hi> and utterly defeats them, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all their Foot, with their Cannon and Ammunition; and Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> himself is brought up Prisoner, as is likewise the Earl of <hi>Holland,</hi> taken at St. <hi>Neots</hi> in <hi>Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington-shire.</hi> The <hi>Kentishmen</hi> scatter'd by Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi>'s Forces at <hi>Maidstone,</hi> cross the <hi>Thames,</hi> and are besieged in <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> which after a generous defence, and great Extremities endured for want of Provision, was surrendred the twenty eighth
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:204203:68"/>of <hi>August</hi> 1648. And the brave Sir <hi>Charles Lucas,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Lisle</hi> shot to death, the Noble Lord <hi>Capel</hi> being reserved for the Scaffold, on which sometime after he triumphantly suffered. There being put to death with him, Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithstanding these successes, the Houses finding the Nation in general breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a settlement, and in order to that not to be satisfied without a <hi>Personal Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> recall their Votes of <hi>non-Addresses,</hi> and thereupon, on the eighteenth of <hi>September</hi> 1648. A Treaty did begin with his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie at <hi>Newport</hi> in the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> whither his Majesty had privately retreated. But before any thing concluded on, some Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Officers publish a Remonstrance dated at St. <hi>Albans</hi> the sixteenth of <hi>November,</hi> signifying their Resolutions to bring the King to Justice (as they pretended) and thereupon some Officers were appointed to seize his Person, and bring him over to <hi>Hurst</hi>-Castle in <hi>Hampshire,</hi> and thence by degrees to <hi>Windsor,</hi> and at last to <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time, they purge the House of all those to whom his Majesties Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Concessions had given satisfaction.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:204203:68"/>Then they erected an unprecedented Court, called <hi>the High Court of Justice,</hi> so named surely either because <hi>Justice</hi> was there <hi>Tryed and Cast,</hi> or else, because they were resolved never to shew <hi>Mercy.</hi> Before these new Judges his Majesty was first brought on the twentieth of <hi>January</hi> 1648. from his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of St. <hi>James</hi>'s, into <hi>Westminster</hi>-Hall. Being under Restraint his appearance could not be avoided, but no Constraint could force him to own their Authority; against which he offered divers unanswera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reasons, but was not permitted to speak them out. However, he plainly told them, that he would not so far betray his Subjects Liberties to submit to their arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and lawless Power, but rather chuse to dye a Martyr for the Protestant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of the Land: so that on <hi>Saturday</hi> the twenty seventh of the same Moneth the President of the Court (one <hi>Bradshaw</hi> a Serjeant at Law, who was never after free from Terror, and Horrors of Conscience to his dying day) proceeded to the horrid Sentence against their Liege Sovereign, that he should be Beheaded, which was Executed before the Banquetting-House at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> on the thirtieth of that Moneth. On which fatal
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:204203:69"/>Morning the Bishop of <hi>London</hi> reading Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with him, and for the first Lesson the twenty seventh Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> being the History of our Saviour's sufferings. The King at first thought the Bishop had chosen the same as suitable to that Juncture, but when he understood that it was the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appointed for that day, he was much comforted with so apt a Remembrance of his Saviours great Example in Sufferings.</p>
               <p>After his Devotions he was led through the Park to <hi>White-hall,</hi> and after some time to the Scaffold, where having declared that he dyed a Martyr for the Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his People, he made a Confession of his Faith, asserting that he dyed a true Son of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> then betook himself to his Private Devotions, and so patiently submitted his Royal Head to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, from the Hand of a disguised Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioner. His body put into a black Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet Coffin, and afterwards wrapt in Lead, was on the seventh of <hi>February</hi> following, Interr'd at St. <hi>George</hi>'s Chappel at <hi>Windsor</hi> in the same Vault with King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, in presence of the Duke of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> Dr. <hi>Juxon</hi> and others, but the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appointed in the Liturgy could not be obtained to be used. Nor had he any Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:204203:69"/>affix'd, but only on the sheet of Lead, on a thin Plate fastned on the Breast, this plain Inscription — King <hi>Charles,</hi> 1648.</p>
               <p>This Pious Prince at the time of his murder had Reigned twenty three Years and ten Moneths, and was then in the nine and fourtieth Year of his Age, having had by his most dear and beloved Queen, in all nine Children, <hi>viz.</hi> first, <hi>Charles-James</hi> born at <hi>Groenwich</hi> the thirteenth of <hi>May</hi> 1629, but died almost as soon as born. Secondly, <hi>Charles</hi> the second our present most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sovereign born at St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>May</hi> the twenty ninth 1630. Thirdly, his Royal Highness <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> born at the same place the thirteenth of <hi>October</hi> 1633. Fourthly, <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Gloucester</hi> born the eighth of <hi>July</hi> 1639. Fifthly, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Mary</hi> born the fourth of <hi>November</hi> 1631. married to <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> the second of <hi>May</hi> 1641. Sixthly, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> born the twenty eighth of <hi>Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 1635. who died with Grief soon after her Father. Seventhly, <hi>Ann</hi> born 17 <hi>March</hi> 1637. died before her father. Eighthly, <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharine</hi> who died almost as soon as born. And lastly <hi>Henrietta</hi> born at <hi>Exeter, June</hi> the sixteenth 1644. since Dutchess of <hi>Orleance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:204203:70"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>The most remarkable Passages in the Reign of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second, hitherto.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUr Gracious Sovereign King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, rightfully began his Reign the thirtieth of <hi>January</hi> 1648. though hindred by the prevailing Rebels from full Exercise of his Authority. He did at that time reside with his Sister the Princess of <hi>Orange</hi> at the <hi>Hague</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and the Rebels at home put out a thing they call'd an Act, to exclude his Successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, taking upon themselves the Title of the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. yet the Kings faithful Subjects did in print proclaim him King in <hi>England,</hi> as did the Lord <hi>Inchequin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and so did the <hi>Scots</hi> too; for whence after much stirr amongst them, some Propositions were sent to the King in <hi>Jersey,</hi> desiring him to sign the solemn League and Covenant, and divers Acts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Treaty between the King and them, at <hi>Breda;</hi> during which the Covenanters in <hi>Scotland</hi> seiz'd the Gallant and Loyal Marquess of <hi>Montross,</hi> and barbarously
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:204203:70"/>hang'd him. Which horrid Insolence was like to have broke off the Treaty, but the Necessity of the King's Affairs forced him at last to agree with their unreasonable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions; and thereupon is invited into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and was afterwards on the first of <hi>January</hi> 1650, Crowned at <hi>Scoon,</hi> being the fourty eighth Monarch of that Kingdom there Crowned.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, <hi>Cromwell</hi> is dispatch'd with an Army by the Parliament into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and on the third of <hi>September</hi> routs the <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> the King himself being at that time at St. <hi>Johnstons,</hi> but afterwards resolv'd to be Generalissimo of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Army himself.</p>
               <p>Whilst these Things were transacting there, the Presbyterians hoping to establish their Covenant and Discipline, began to hold some Correspondence with the Kings Friends; and several of their most eminent Ministers engaged in the Design, of whom, two, that is to say, Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gibbons</hi> were put to Death, Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> presented four Petitions to the Parliament for his Life, the last of which was as follows.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:204203:71"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Supream Authority, the Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>Christopher Love,</hi> a condemned Prisoner in the Tower of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THat your Petitioner doth humbly adore the wonderful Goodness of God, and most thankfully acknowledg the great Mercy of the Parliament for so seasonable and acceptable an Act of Grace to such an offended Suppliant, that when there was but a step between him and Death, the number of his days being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished, and he almost cut off from the Land of the living, then you mercifully inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, and gave him his Life for a Moneth longer, which was to him as a Resurrection from the dead. The Consideration whereof melteth the Heart of your Petitioner, and makes him (after a more narrow search into his Heart and Wayes) more deeply sensible than ever of his Sin against God, aad more sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:204203:71"/>for his high Crimes and Offences against the Parliament, in his late and great Miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>He humbly acknowledgeth be hath so highly violated the Laws of the Common-wealth, as that thereby he hath rendred himself Guilty of the Sentence of Death, justly passed on him by the High Court of Justice. He doth also herewith humbly Offer to your Honours a free and full Narrative under his band of the whole Design (to the best of his Remembrance) which he leaveth to your Grave Wisdomes and favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Interpretations, fully resolved that he will neither Plot, Contrive, or design any thing prejudicial to the present Government. But will in his Place and Calling oppose any Designs whatsoever (whether in this or the Neighbour Nation) that may tend to the Ruine of this Common-wealth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Your dying Petitioner with all humble im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity prostrates himself at your feet, puts his mouth in the dust, (O that there may be Hope!) craving your ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy, begging his Life at your hands, promising never to imploy that Life against you he shall receive from you; but doth hold it his duty to his place and calling, to lay out himself for
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:204203:72"/>the glory of God, the good of his People, the peace and safety of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And your Petitioner shall ever pray, &amp;c.</hi> CHRISTOPHER. LOVE.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <trailer>Read Aug. <hi>14. 1651.</hi> Read again Aug. <hi>16. 1651.</hi>
                        </trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But notwithstanding all these Submissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and passionate Intreaties, the pretended Parliament was deaf, and on the 22th. of <hi>August</hi> 1651. brought him to the Block on <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> where at the same time one <hi>Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons</hi> suffered with him. The rest concerned were pardoned.</p>
            <p>The third of <hi>September</hi> 1651. happened the fatal Battel at <hi>Worcester,</hi> His Majesty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving suddenly slipt by <hi>Cromwel</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and so marched directly for <hi>England;</hi> but the other followed him close, and the County Troops being every where raised, His Majesties Forces were overpowered, though in his own Royal Person he gave them most signal examples of Courage, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Horse twice that day shot under
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:204203:72"/>him. After this Defeat His Majesty, getting away with much difficulty, retired to a Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers house in <hi>Stafford-shire,</hi> and there chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Habit, and suffering his Royal Locks to be cut off with a Knife, for want of a more convenient Instrument: But not thinking himself safe there, there being a Thousand pounds offered to any that could take him, he took Sanctuary in that famous Oke, ever since dignified with the Title of <hi>Royal,</hi> standing in a Wood about 4 miles from <hi>Woolver-hampton,</hi> where he remained some days without any Company, save of one friend that towards night brought him Provision. As soon as might be he remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from thence to the house of Mrs. <hi>Jane Lane,</hi> an eminent Instrument in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance beyond Sea, whither at last after a thousand dangers, protected by Providence, he safely got, passing in a small Vessel from <hi>Sussex</hi> to <hi>New Haven</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1652. the <hi>Hogan Mogan</hi> State scorning to truckle to our Infant Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, a War broke out between us and <hi>Holland,</hi> wherein the <hi>English</hi> having the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in five several sharp Engagements at Sea, in one of which their excellent Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Van Tromp</hi> the Elder was slain, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that Republick brought to great distress:
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:204203:73"/>But afterwards on a sudden a dishonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Peace was clapt up by that grand Usurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> for his own ends, and the securing of his Usurpations; he having first on the 20th: of <hi>April</hi> 1653. by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable power of his Sword dissolved his good Masters the remainder of the Long Parliament.</p>
            <p>On the 5th. of <hi>July</hi> in the year last men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned began the little sanctified Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at <hi>Westminster,</hi> called <hi>The Fanatick Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in which nothing (but some moneths time and Canting) having pass'd, on the 12th. of <hi>December</hi> following they were turn'd out of doors too by mighty <hi>Oliver,</hi> who 4 days after usurp'd more than the power of a King under the Title of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</p>
            <p>On the third of <hi>September</hi> 1654. another thing called a Parliament was assembled, who beginning to question the Lawfulness of the Power by which they were called, were in some short time likewise sent packing.</p>
            <p>And now began the War with <hi>Spain,</hi> on pretence of injuries to our Merchants, and Hardships to <hi>English</hi> Protestants to be design'd; for in the beginning of the year 1655. was the unfortunate Expedition to <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> which by ill Conduct miscarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:204203:73"/>however in their return they took the Island of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> which has ever since re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in <hi>English</hi> hands, and is now become a flourishing Plantation.</p>
            <p>On the 17th. of <hi>September</hi> 1656. comes another Mock-Parliament, with the Pagean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>The other House</hi> for the House of Lords, in which <hi>Cromwel</hi> secretly used great endeavours to be made King, and by his Creatures in the Houses was petitioned to accept that Title: but he having sounded the business, and not finding it fordable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Army was so averse, did not think fit to venture upon't, and so publickly refused what he mainly pursued.</p>
            <p>The later end of the same year was the Trial and Sentence of <hi>James Nailor,</hi> the Ringleader of the Quakers, who about <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stol</hi> had assumed to himself Divine Honours, and for his Blasphemies was first whipt, then had his Tongue bored through with a red hot Iron, and the Letter <hi>B</hi> branded in his Forehead.</p>
            <p>In 1657. <hi>Cromwel</hi> carried on the War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Spain</hi> vigorously at Sea, General <hi>Blake</hi> the 22th. of <hi>April</hi> with wonderful Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try destroying their Plate Fleet in the Bay of <hi>Sancta Cruz.</hi> Besides which assisting the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> with 6000 men, <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:204203:74"/>was taken, which was put into <hi>English</hi> hands. During these times there were ever and anon Plots forsooth discovered, some real, but more contrived to vex and fleece the poor Cavaliers: Of whom, on that score, towards the end of his Usurpation suffered the Reverend Dr. <hi>Hewet,</hi> and the noble Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby,</hi> being beheaded on <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> and three more drawn, hang'd, and quarter'd.</p>
            <p>But now this blazing Meteor, that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended so much evil to the World, which to make good the Presage it self effected, must disappear; for on Friday the third of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> (famous to him for his two Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at <hi>Dunbar</hi> and <hi>Worcester</hi>) in the year 1658. about three of the clock in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, died <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> our Protector, (God ever protect us from the like) that day being ushered in with a night as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestuous, as had been known within the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of Man.</p>
            <p>His Son <hi>Richard</hi> took upon him to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in his Place and Title, and had a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of his own, and received numerous Addresses, calling him the <hi>Joshua</hi> that was to succeed their <hi>Moses,</hi> and that they would live and die with him, &amp;c. but all prov'd Lies, for in <hi>May</hi> following, the Army ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:204203:74"/>by <hi>Fleetwood</hi> and <hi>Lambert,</hi> calling in the old Members of the Long Parliament, interrupted by his Father in 1653, he was quietly laid aside, and under his hand sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to their Power. A Person chiefly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy in being the Son of such a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>During this Dominion of the reviv'd Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of a Parliament (thence commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Rump</hi>) about Harvest-time 1659. Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> and divers other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men appeared for the King; but failing of the expected Assistances, were overcome by <hi>Lambert,</hi> who desirous to tread <hi>Olivers</hi> steps, turn'd out the Rump once again; and now the Thing to govern the Nation was called <hi>A Council of Safety,</hi> consisting of 23 Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, for the most part Army-Officers. Things being in this confusion, the gallant <hi>Monk</hi> (inspir'd by Providence) thought it a convenient opportunity to stir, under the pretext of restoring the late remnant Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and though in the depth of Winter 1659, marches into <hi>England. Lambert</hi> goes with a strong Army to oppose him, but in his absence the Rump once more gets to roost, and dissolves his Committee of Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, so that he being deserted by his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Monk</hi> victorious without striking a
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:204203:75"/>stroke marches his Army to <hi>London,</hi> out of which when he came near, he had prudently caused the other Forces to be withdrawn. All the way he was courted in every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with Addresses, but behaved himself still with that admirable Conduct and Secrecy, as was necessary for so great and glorious a Design as he was engaged in. However ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving some suspitions to cast him into dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favour with the City, the Rump put him upon the unpleasing course of pulling down their Gates, &amp;c. But the very next day he fully satisfied the City by declaring for a Free Parliament, and causing the <hi>Secluded Members</hi> (that is, a great number of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-men, which many years before had been illegally thrust out of the House, because they would not joyn in the mischievous Votes of the rest, tending to the Murther of the late King) to be now readmitted to their places, who having made some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress in the work, dissolved themselves, sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning a new Parliament to succeed them on the 25th. of <hi>April</hi> 1660, who being met, proceeded with such expedition to give publick testimony of their Loyalty, that on the eighth of <hi>May</hi> His Majesty our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sovereign was proclaimed, to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal satisfaction of the People, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:204203:75"/>the same with all imaginable demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of Joy.</p>
            <p>To complete which on the 29th. of the same Moneth (being his Royal Birth-day) arrived in <hi>England,</hi> and with him Happiness and Order to these three long-distracted Kingdoms; for the re-settlement of which His Majesty was most zealous in promoting and hastening the Act of Indempnity, which passed on the 29th. of <hi>August</hi> following.</p>
            <p>On the 13th. of <hi>September</hi> 1660. died that most vertuous and hopeful Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Duke of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> the Kings younger Brother, in the 21th. year of his age; and about Christmass following his incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sister <hi>Mary</hi> Princess of <hi>Aurange</hi> (Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Prince now living) who was come over to visit the King her dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fell sick and died, to the infinite grief of His Majesty and the Court, she being bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the 29th. of <hi>December.</hi> On which day the Parliament was dissolved, which (as His Majesty most prophetically told them) will to all posterity be celebrated by the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>THE HEALING AND BLESSED PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Jan.</hi> 1660. <hi>Venner</hi> a Wine-Cooper by Trade, and a Fifth-Monarchy man by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, with about 30 of his desperate Gang,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:204203:76"/>broke out into a most Fanatick Rebellion in the City of <hi>London,</hi> in quelling of whom se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral people were slain, and the said <hi>Venner</hi> and 11 of his Accomplices afterwards exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            <p>The 23th. day of <hi>April</hi> 1661, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty was crowned; and the 8th. of <hi>May</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing a new Parliament was called, and with it a Convocation of the Clergy, who confirmed the Form of the Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er formerly established.</p>
            <p>The 22th. of <hi>May</hi> 1662. the King marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lady <hi>Catarina, Infanta</hi> of <hi>Portugal.</hi> And the 14th. of <hi>June</hi> following Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> was beheaded on Tower-hill: <hi>John Lambert</hi> at the same time was tried, but by the Kings mercy had his Life pardoned; we wish he may never forget so gracious a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, nor again tempt his own Fate by sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequent Crimes.</p>
            <p>Towards the end of the year 1664. and the beginning of 65. three several Comets or Blazing Stars appeared in the Heavens; nor were the events unsuitable to the Presages, for immediately after happened the first, or if you account that before the Kings Return, the second <hi>Dutch</hi> War, the lamentable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion, and the dreadful Fire in <hi>London,</hi> of each of which I shall give you a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:204203:76"/>
            <p> In 1664. Preparations were made for War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and to provoke us <hi>Bankert</hi> their Admiral brav'd it with his Squadron in our very River; but no grand Engagement happened till the third of <hi>Juno</hi> 1665. when the <hi>English</hi> Fleet under the Duke of <hi>York</hi> obtained a signal Victory, the <hi>Dutch</hi> losing 20 Sail of Ships, and 4000 Men kill'd and wounded, and their Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Opdam</hi> blown up. On our side we lost the Lords <hi>Falmouth, Muscarry, Portland, Marl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> Mr. <hi>Boil,</hi> Sir <hi>John Lawson,</hi> and Rear-Admiral <hi>Sansom,</hi> and not above 500 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people.</p>
            <p>On the 10th. of <hi>February</hi> following a War was declared against <hi>France,</hi> but in the mean time we have a more dreadful Enemy than either of them both to grapple with, to wit, a most devouring Pestilence, which began to be taken notice of in <hi>May</hi> 1665, one weeks Bill having then 9 in it of the Plague, which much alarm'd people; but the next week it decreasing to 3, their fears abate; but next week it swells to 14, then to 17, next to 43, and so continually all <hi>June, July, &amp;c.</hi> till at the later end of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> there died within the Bills of Mortality 6102, of the Plague onely in one week, and afterwards in the third week of <hi>September</hi>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:204203:77"/>(which was the highest Bill of all) the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber did arise to 7165. From which time it abated till towards <hi>January,</hi> and then the City was wholly free; there dying that year within the Bills of Mortality of the Plague (as is verily believed) One hundred thousand. In the mean time the Court and Parliament retire to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and there grant the King Twelve hundred and fifty thousand pounds to carry on the War.</p>
            <p>In the year 1666. our Fleet put to Sea, under Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marl,</hi> and the former being gone with a Squadron to intercept the <hi>French</hi> Fleet which was expected, the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the mean time come up with the later, who on the first of <hi>June,</hi> with the disadvantage of but 54 Sail against 91 of the Enemy enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them, who were reinforced next day with another Recruit, so that he was forced to fight them two days together, till the Prince came up, and then after a sharp Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute for almost a whole day, they fled, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us Masters of the Sea, though much shattered and considerable loss, which on their side was nothing inferiour. In this fight Sir <hi>George Ascough</hi> was taken.</p>
            <p>On the 25 and 26 of <hi>July</hi> happened an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Engagement, wherein the <hi>English</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:204203:77"/>an indisputable Victory; the <hi>Dutch</hi> taking shelter in their Sands, and soon after Sir <hi>Robert Holmes</hi> burnt 150 of their Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Ships in the <hi>Vly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the second of <hi>September</hi> 1666. being Sunday, about two of the clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing began the dreadful fire in a Bakers house by <hi>Pudding-lane</hi> near <hi>Fish-street Hill,</hi> which soon invaded St. <hi>Magnes</hi> Church, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed it; then it burnt down a great stack of Building on the Bridge, but being happily stopt from further progress that way, runs along <hi>Thames-street</hi> Westward, having got as far that night as <hi>Garlick-hithe,</hi> and crept up into <hi>Cannon-street.</hi> On the Monday <hi>Grace-church street</hi> and part of <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church street</hi> are all in flames, which making way into <hi>Cornhill</hi> consume that stately street, together with the Royal Exchange. On Monday night the Fire works backwards strangely against the wind beyond <hi>Belins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> and up to <hi>Tower-street;</hi> Westward it comes to <hi>Dowgate</hi> and <hi>Watling-street,</hi> and so proceeds as a Conqueror into <hi>Cheapside.</hi> On Tuesday <hi>Cheapside</hi> and the streets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiguous, as <hi>Soper-lane, Bow-lane, Bread-street,</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, <hi>Pater noster Row,</hi> and <hi>Ludgate</hi> submit to its fury; and <hi>Guild-hall</hi> as a Palace of burnish'd Brass stands for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:204203:78"/>hours like one bright burning coal, a most amazing Spectacle. On Wednesday morning the Fire receives some check at <hi>Leaden-hall,</hi> the <hi>Temple, &amp;c.</hi> wherein blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of houses was very instrumental; and on Thursday the Flames were extinguish'd, having consumed 87 Parishes within the Walls, and done much damage in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs.</p>
            <p>The 29 <hi>June</hi> 1667. was concluded a Peace at <hi>Breda</hi> between the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch;</hi> but before the same was ratified they did us some mischief at <hi>Chatham,</hi> and carried away with them the <hi>Jonathan</hi> a small <hi>Dutch</hi> Prize, and the Hull of the <hi>Royal Charles;</hi> an Exploit whereof they have little to brag, being rather fortunate than wise, for 'twas a million to one that it had not miscarried and endangered all their Fleet.</p>
            <p>The 31 <hi>Aug.</hi> 1669. died the Queen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>England</hi> at St. <hi>Colomb</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> and on the fourth of <hi>January</hi> following His Grace <hi>George Monk</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 20 <hi>Iune</hi> 1670. died the Dutchess of <hi>Orleans,</hi> presently after her return from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Visit to her Brother the King of <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the beginning of 1672. began the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Dutch</hi> War, and the 28th. of <hi>May</hi> the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:204203:78"/>
               <hi>Dutch</hi> are beaten by the <hi>English</hi> Fleet under the Duke of <hi>York</hi> at <hi>Sould-bay,</hi> where the Earl of <hi>Sandwich</hi> was unfortunately lost. In 1673. Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> commanded the Fleet, who likewise on 28 <hi>May</hi> fought the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and made them retreat. And so he did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain on 4 <hi>Iune</hi> following, and obtained an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Victory on the 11 <hi>August,</hi> but not without losing that expert Sea-Commander Sir <hi>Edward Spragg;</hi> and in <hi>Ianuary</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Peace was concluded with <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On 20 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1675. the far greater part of that eminent Corporation of <hi>Northampton</hi> was burnt down to the ground. The like sad fate on 26 <hi>May</hi> 1676. befell the Borough of <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus have we with as much fulness and plainness as might consist with our designed bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, given you an account of the most remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble occurrences in the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>both before and since the Conquest down to our Times, which leaving to the courteous entertainment of the Reader, I shall conclude this Epitome of English History with hearty prayers, That God would long preserve the Monarchy of</hi> Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>protect the person of our Gracious Sovereign, and continue in full splendour amongst us the true Protestant Religion, in spight of all publick Enemies or private Confederacies whatsoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>